Home
Methods
Background
Texts
Results

Methods

Our Process

Each group member was given specific stories from one of the three texts to read, each one connecting to one of the other texts in some way, often through a shared character. We focused on a number of recurring themes explained below, marking them up using criteria we had previously agreed on, and then proofread each other's markup before using it to create the filtering system.

Elements and General Attributes

The elements we used, as well as their criteria for use, as described below.

God - this element was used every time the text referenced God, including when he was not the subject. The element went around both the word "God" and the context within the sentence.

Love - this element was used when the word "love" was explicitly mentioned, or when a person was acting or commanded to act in a loving way. The attributes "others" "God" and "idols" were used to clarify the recipient of the love.

Respect - this element was used when the word "respect" was used, or when an action or behavior seemed respecful in a more theoretical sence. As this element was particularly ambiguous, we made sure to pay special attention to it while proofreading.

Worship - this element was used when the characters in the text were praising God

Blessings - this element was used when the text literally said "blessings," as well as when miracles (generally from Jesus) were bestowed upon a person.

Heaven and Hell - these elements were used when the words "heaven" or "hell" were explicity mentioned, or when the text was clearly talking about one or the other.

Tone Attributes

In addition to the more straightforward elements, attributes were used to clarify the tone of the God element. These are explained below.

Creator - this attribute was used within the creation story.

Wrathful - this attrubute was used in instances when god is portrayed as vengeful, as long as the action was coming from God

Fear of - by contrast, this attribute was used to signify fear of God coming from humanity, and although the contexts in which the two were used were similar, this arrtibute requires the action to come from a person or people.

Loving - this attribute was used when the word "grace" was used in referece to God, or when he was showing affection towards humans or humanity.

Powerful - this attribute was used when God was portrayed as greater than others, or when words and phrases such as "almighty God' and "God commanded" were used.

Merciful - this attribute was used when the word "mercy: was used, or when God made the choice not to punish someone

Christian Scripture

Jesus

Luke

Verse 1:1: Forasmuch as many have taken in hand to set forth in order a declaration of those things which are most surely believed among us,

Verse 1:2: Even as they delivered them unto us, which from the beginning were eyewitnesses, and ministers of the word;

Verse 1:3: It seemed good to me also, having had perfect understanding of all things from the very first, to write unto thee in order, most excellent Theophilus,

Verse 1:4:That thou mightest know the certainty of those things That thou mightest know the certainty of those things, wherein thou hast been instructed.

Verse 1:5: There was in the days of Herod, the king of Judaea, a certain priest named Zacharias, of the course of Abia: and his wife [was] of the daughters of Aaron, and her name [was] Elisabeth.

Verse 1:6:And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless.

Verse 1:7: And they had no child, because that Elisabeth was barren, and they both were [now] well stricken in years.

Verse 1:8: while he executed the priest’s office before God in the order of his course And it came to pass, that while he executed the priest’s office before God in the order of his course,

Verse 1:9: According to the custom of the priest’s office, his lot was to burn incense when he went into the temple of the Lord.

Verse 1:10: And the whole multitude of the people were praying without at the time of incense.

Verse 1:11: And there appeared unto him an angel of the Lord standing on the right side of the altar of incense.

Verse 1:12:And when Zacharias saw [him,] he was troubled, and fear fell upon him And when Zacharias saw [him,] he was troubled, and fear fell upon him.

Verse 1:13:said unto him, Fear not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard; and thy wife Elisabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John But the angel said unto him, Fear not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard; and thy wife Elisabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John.

Verse 1:14: And thou shalt have joy and gladness; and many shall rejoice at his birth.

Verse 1:15:For he shall be great in the sight of the Lord For he shall be great in the sight of the Lord, and shall drink neither wine nor strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Ghost, even from his mother’s womb.

Verse 1:16: And many of the children of Israel shall he turn to the Lord their God.

Verse 1:17: And he shall go before him in the spirit and power of Elias, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just; to make ready a people prepared for the Lord.

Verse 1:18: And Zacharias said unto the angel, Whereby shall I know this? for I am an old man, and my wife well stricken in years.

Verse 1:19: >And the angel answering said unto him, I am Gabriel, that stand in the presence of God; and am sent to speak unto thee, and to shew thee these glad tidings.

Verse 1:20:And, behold, thou shalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that these things shall be performed, because thou believest not my words, which shall be fulfilled in their season. And, behold, thou shalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that these things shall be performed, because thou believest not my words, which shall be fulfilled in their season.

Verse 1:21: And the people waited for Zacharias, and marvelled that he tarried so long in the temple.

Verse 1:22: And when he came out, he could not speak unto them: and they perceived that he had seen a vision in the temple: for he beckoned unto them, and remained speechless.

Verse 1:23: And it came to pass, that, as soon as the days of his ministration were accomplished, he departed to his own house.

Verse 1:24: And after those days his wife Elisabeth conceived, and hid herself five months, saying,

Verse 1:25: Thus hath the Lord dealt with me in the days wherein he looked on [me,] to take away my reproach among men.

Verse 1:26:the angel Gabriel was sent from God unto a city of Galilee, named Nazareth And in the sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent from God unto a city of Galilee, named Nazareth,

Verse 1:27: To a virgin espoused to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the virgin’s name [was] Mary.

Verse 1:28: And the angel came in unto her, and said, Hail, [thou that art] highly favoured, the Lord [is] with thee: blessed [art] thou among women.

Verse 1:29: And when she saw [him,] she was troubled at his saying, and cast in her mind what manner of salutation this should be.

Verse 1:30:Fear not, Maryfor thou hast found favour with God And the angel said unto her, Fear not, Mary: for thou hast found favour with God.

Verse 1:31: And, behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a son, and shalt call his name JESUS.

Verse 1:32:He shall be great, and shall be called the Son of the Highest: and the Lord God shall give unto him the throne of his father David He shall be great, and shall be called the Son of the Highest: and the Lord God shall give unto him the throne of his father David:

Verse 1:33: And he shall reign over the house of Jacob for ever; and of his kingdom there shall be no end.

Verse 1:34: Then said Mary unto the angel, How shall this be, seeing I know not a man?

Verse 1:35: And the angel answered and said unto her, The Holy Ghost shall come upon thee, and the power of the Highest shall overshadow thee: therefore also that holy thing which shall be born of thee shall be called the Son of God.

Verse 1:36: And, behold, thy cousin Elisabeth, she hath also conceived a son in her old age: and this is the sixth month with her, who was called barren.

Verse 1:37:For with God nothing shall be impossible For with God nothing shall be impossible.

Verse 1:38: And Mary said, Behold the handmaid of the Lord; be it unto me according to thy word. And the angel departed from her.

Verse 1:39: And Mary arose in those days, and went into the hill country with haste, into a city of Juda;

Verse 1:40: And entered into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elisabeth.

Verse 1:41: And it came to pass, that, when Elisabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe leaped in her womb; and Elisabeth was filled with the Holy Ghost:

Verse 1:42: And she spake out with a loud voice, and said, Blessed [art] thou among women, and blessed [is] the fruit of thy womb.

Verse 1:43: And whence [is] this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me?

Verse 1:44: For, lo, as soon as the voice of thy salutation sounded in mine ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy.

Verse 1:45: And blessed [is] she that believed: for there shall be a performance of those things which were told her from the Lord.

Verse 1:46: And Mary said, My soul doth magnify the Lord,

Verse 1:47: And my spirit hath rejoiced in God my Saviour.

Verse 1:48: For he hath regarded the low estate of his handmaiden: for, behold, from henceforth all generations shall call me blessed.

Verse 1:49: For he that is mighty hath done to me great things; and holy [is] his name.

Verse 1:50:mercyfear him from generation to generation And his mercy [is] on them that fear him from generation to generation.

Verse 1:51:He hath shewed strength with his arm; he hath scattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts He hath shewed strength with his arm; he hath scattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts.

Verse 1:52:He hath put down the mighty from [their] seats, and exalted them of low degree He hath put down the mighty from [their] seats, and exalted them of low degree.

Verse 1:53:He hath filled the hungry with good things; and the rich he hath sent empty away He hath filled the hungry with good things; and the rich he hath sent empty away.

Verse 1:54:He hath holpen his servant Israel, in remembrance of [his] mercy He hath holpen his servant Israel, in remembrance of [his] mercy;

Verse 1:55: As he spake to our fathers, to Abraham, and to his seed for ever.

Verse 1:56: And Mary abode with her about three months, and returned to her own house.

Verse 1:57: Now Elisabeth’s full time came that she should be delivered; and she brought forth a son.

Verse 1:58:her cousins heard how the Lord had shewed great mercy upon her; and they rejoiced with her And her neighbours and her cousins heard how the Lord had shewed great mercy upon her; and they rejoiced with her.

Verse 1:59: And it came to pass, that on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child; and they called him Zacharias, after the name of his father.

Verse 1:60: And his mother answered and said, Not [so;] but he shall be called John.

Verse 1:61: And they said unto her, There is none of thy kindred that is called by this name.

Verse 1:62: And they made signs to his father, how he would have him called.

Verse 1:63: And he asked for a writing table, and wrote, saying, His name is John. And they marvelled all.

Verse 1:64: And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue [loosed,] and he spake, and praised God.

Verse 1:65:And fear came on all that dwelt round about them: and all these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill country of Judaea And fear came on all that dwelt round about them: and all these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill country of Judaea.

Verse 1:66: And all they that heard [them] laid [them] up in their hearts, saying, What manner of child shall this be! And the hand of the Lord was with him.

Verse 1:67: And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Ghost, and prophesied, saying,

Verse 1:68: Blessed [be] the Lord God of Israel; for he hath visited and redeemed his people,

Verse 1:69: And hath raised up an horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David;

Verse 1:70: As he spake by the mouth of his holy prophets, which have been since the world began:

Verse 1:71:That we should be saved from our enemies, and from the hand of all that hate us That we should be saved from our enemies, and from the hand of all that hate us;

Verse 1:72:To perform the mercy [promised] to our fathers, and to remember his holy covenant To perform the mercy [promised] to our fathers, and to remember his holy covenant;

Verse 1:73: The oath which he sware to our father Abraham,

Verse 1:74:That he would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hand of our enemies might serve him without fear That he would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hand of our enemies might serve him without fear,

Verse 1:75: In holiness and righteousness before him, all the days of our life.

Verse 1:76: And thou, child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest: for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to prepare his ways;

Verse 1:77: To give knowledge of salvation unto his people by the remission of their sins,

Verse 1:78:Through the tender mercy of our God; whereby the dayspring from on high hath visited us Through the tender mercy of our God; whereby the dayspring from on high hath visited us,

Verse 1:79:To give light to them that sit in darkness and [in] the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace To give light to them that sit in darkness and [in] the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace.

Verse 1:80: And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, and was in the deserts till the day of his shewing unto Israel.

Luke

Verse 2:1: And it came to pass in those days, that there went out a decree from Caesar Augustus, that all the world should be taxed.

Verse 2:2: ([And] this taxing was first made when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.)

Verse 2:3: And all went to be taxed, every one into his own city.

Verse 2:4: And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judaea, unto the city of David, which is called Bethlehem; (because he was of the house and lineage of David:)

Verse 2:5: To be taxed with Mary his espoused wife, being great with child.

Verse 2:6: And so it was, that, while they were there, the days were accomplished that she should be delivered.

Verse 2:7: And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn.

Verse 2:8: And there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.

Verse 2:9: And, lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about them: and they were sore afraid.

Verse 2:10:Fear not behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people And the angel said unto them, Fear not: for, behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people.

Verse 2:11: For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord.

Verse 2:12: And this [shall be] a sign unto you; Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, lying in a manger.

Verse 2:13: And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying,

Verse 2:14: Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will toward men.

Verse 2:15: And it came to pass, as the angels were gone away from them into heaven, the shepherds said one to another, Let us now go even unto Bethlehem, and see this thing which is come to pass, which the Lord hath made known unto us.

Verse 2:16: And they came with haste, and found Mary, and Joseph, and the babe lying in a manger.

Verse 2:17: And when they had seen [it,] they made known abroad the saying which was told them concerning this child.

Verse 2:18: And all they that heard [it] wondered at those things which were told them by the shepherds.

Verse 2:19: But Mary kept all these things, and pondered [them] in her heart.

Verse 2:20: And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, as it was told unto them.

Verse 2:21: And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called JESUS, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.

Verse 2:22: And when the days of her purification according to the law of Moses were accomplished, they brought him to Jerusalem, to present [him] to the Lord;

Verse 2:23: (As it is written in the law of the Lord, Every male that openeth the womb shall be called holy to the Lord;)

Verse 2:24: And to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord, A pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons.

Verse 2:25: And, behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name [was] Simeon; and the same man [was] just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel: and the Holy Ghost was upon him.

Verse 2:26: And it was revealed unto him by the Holy Ghost, that he should not see death, before he had seen the Lord’s Christ.

Verse 2:27: And he came by the Spirit into the temple: and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him after the custom of the law,

Verse 2:28: Then took he him up in his arms, and blessed God, and said,

Verse 2:29: Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, according to thy word:

Verse 2:30: For mine eyes have seen thy salvation,

Verse 2:31: Which thou hast prepared before the face of all people;

Verse 2:32: A light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people Israel.

Verse 2:33: And Joseph and his mother marvelled at those things which were spoken of him.

Verse 2:34:Behold, this [child] is set for the fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against And Simeon blessed them, and said unto Mary his mother, Behold, this [child] is set for the fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against;

Verse 2:35: (Yea, a sword shall pierce through thy own soul also,) that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed.

Verse 2:36: And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Aser: she was of a great age, and had lived with an husband seven years from her virginity;

Verse 2:37: And she [was] a widow of about fourscore and four years, which departed not from the temple, but served [God] with fastings and prayers night and day.

Verse 2:38: And she coming in that instant gave thanks likewise unto the Lord, and spake of him to all them that looked for redemption in Jerusalem.

Verse 2:39: And when they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned into Galilee, to their own city Nazareth.

Verse 2:40:And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him.

Verse 2:41: Now his parents went to Jerusalem every year at the feast of the passover.

Verse 2:42: And when he was twelve years old, they went up to Jerusalem after the custom of the feast.

Verse 2:43: And when they had fulfilled the days, as they returned, the child Jesus tarried behind in Jerusalem; and Joseph and his mother knew not [of it. ]

Verse 2:44: But they, supposing him to have been in the company, went a day’s journey; and they sought him among [their] kinsfolk and acquaintance.

Verse 2:45: And when they found him not, they turned back again to Jerusalem, seeking him.

Verse 2:46: And it came to pass, that after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the doctors, both hearing them, and asking them questions.

Verse 2:47: And all that heard him were astonished at his understanding and answers.

Verse 2:48: And when they saw him, they were amazed: and his mother said unto him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing.

Verse 2:49: And he said unto them, How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father’s business?

Verse 2:50: And they understood not the saying which he spake unto them.

Verse 2:51: And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was subject unto them: but his mother kept all these sayings in her heart.

Verse 2:52: And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man.

John

Verse 2:1: And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there:

Verse 2:2: And both Jesus was called, and his disciples, to the marriage.

Verse 2:3: And when they wanted wine, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine.

Verse 2:4: Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come.

Verse 2:5: His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do [it. ]

Verse 2:6: And there were set there six waterpots of stone, after the manner of the purifying of the Jews, containing two or three firkins apiece.

Verse 2:7: Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim.

Verse 2:8: And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the governor of the feast. And they bare [it. ]

Verse 2:9: When the ruler of the feast had tasted the water that was made wine, and knew not whence it was: (but the servants which drew the water knew;) the governor of the feast called the bridegroom,

Verse 2:10: And saith unto him, Every man at the beginning doth set forth good wine; and when men have well drunk, then that which is worse: [but] thou hast kept the good wine until now.

Verse 2:11: This beginning of miracles did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested forth his glory; and his disciples believed on him.

Matthew

Verse 3:13: Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to Jordan unto John, to be baptized of him.

Verse 3:14: But John forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou to me?

Verse 3:15:Suffer [it to be so] now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffered him And Jesus answering said unto him, Suffer [it to be so] now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffered him.

Verse 3:16: And Jesus, when he was baptized, went up straightway out of the water: and, lo, the heavens were opened unto him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove, and lighting upon him:

Verse 3:17: This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased And lo a voice from heaven, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.

Luke

Verse 8:22: Now it came to pass on a certain day, that he went into a ship with his disciples: and he said unto them, Let us go over unto the other side of the lake. And they launched forth.

Verse 8:23: But as they sailed he fell asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filled [with water,] and were in jeopardy.

Verse 8:24:Then he arose, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish. Then he arose, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm.

Verse 8:25:And he said unto them, Where is your faith? And they being afraid wondered, saying one to another, What manner of man is this! And he said unto them, Where is your faith? And they being afraid wondered, saying one to another, What manner of man is this! for he commandeth even the winds and water, and they obey him.

John

Verse 19:1: Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged [him. ]

Verse 19:2: And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put [it] on his head, and they put on him a purple robe,

Verse 19:3: And said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they smote him with their hands.

Verse 19:4: Pilate therefore went forth again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him.

Verse 19:5: Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And [Pilate] saith unto them, Behold the man!

Verse 19:6: When the chief priests therefore and officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify [him,] crucify [him.] Pilate saith unto them, Take ye him, and crucify [him:] for I find no fault in him.

Verse 19:7: The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God.

Verse 19:8: When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he was the more afraid;

Verse 19:9: And went again into the judgment hall, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer.

Verse 19:10: Then saith Pilate unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee, and have power to release thee?

Verse 19:11:Thou couldest have no power [at all] against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin Jesus answered, Thou couldest have no power [at all] against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin.

Verse 19:12: And from thenceforth Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Caesar’s friend: whosoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar.

Verse 19:13: When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus forth, and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew, Gabbatha.

Verse 19:14: And it was the preparation of the passover, and about the sixth hour: and he saith unto the Jews, Behold your King!

Verse 19:15: But they cried out, Away with [him,] away with [him,] crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.

Verse 19:16: Then delivered he him therefore unto them to be crucified. And they took Jesus, and led [him] away.

Verse 19:17: And he bearing his cross went forth into a place called [the place] of a skull, which is called in the Hebrew Golgotha:

Verse 19:18: Where they crucified him, and two others with him, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst.

Verse 19:19: And Pilate wrote a title, and put [it] on the cross. And the writing was, JESUS OF NAZARETH THE KING OF THE JEWS.

Verse 19:20: This title then read many of the Jews: for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city: and it was written in Hebrew, [and] Greek, [and] Latin.

Verse 19:21: Then said the chief priests of the Jews to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews.

Verse 19:22: Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.

Verse 19:23: Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments, and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also [his] coat: now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.

Verse 19:24: They said therefore among themselves, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith, They parted my raiment among them, and for my vesture they did cast lots. These things therefore the soldiers did.

Verse 19:25: Now there stood by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother’s sister, Mary the [wife] of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.

Verse 19:26: When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son!

Verse 19:27: Then saith he to the disciple, Behold thy mother! And from that hour that disciple took her unto his own [home. ]

Verse 19:28: After this, Jesus knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst.

Verse 19:29: Now there was set a vessel full of vinegar: and they filled a spunge with vinegar, and put [it] upon hyssop, and put [it] to his mouth.

Verse 19:30:It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost.

Verse 19:31: The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and [that] they might be taken away.

Verse 19:32: Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him.

Verse 19:33: But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs:

Verse 19:34: But one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and forthwith came there out blood and water.

Verse 19:35: And he that saw [it] bare record, and his record is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye might believe.

Verse 19:36: For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken.

Verse 19:37: And again another scripture saith, They shall look on him whom they pierced.

Verse 19:38: And after this Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, besought Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave [him] leave. He came therefore, and took the body of Jesus.

Verse 19:39: And there came also Nicodemus, which at the first came to Jesus by night, and brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about an hundred pound [weight. ]

Verse 19:40: Then took they the body of Jesus, and wound it in linen clothes with the spices, as the manner of the Jews is to bury.

Verse 19:41: Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new sepulchre, wherein was never man yet laid.

Verse 19:42: There laid they Jesus therefore because of the Jews’ preparation [day;] for the sepulchre was nigh at hand.

Luke

Verse 23:26: And as they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon, a Cyrenian, coming out of the country, and on him they laid the cross, that he might bear [it] after Jesus.

Verse 23:27: And there followed him a great company of people, and of women, which also bewailed and lamented him.

Verse 23:28:Jesus turning unto them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children But Jesus turning unto them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children.

Verse 23:29: For, behold, the days are coming, in the which they shall say, Blessed [are] the barren, and the wombs that never bare, and the paps which never gave suck.

Verse 23:30: Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us.

Verse 23:31: For if they do these things in a green tree, what shall be done in the dry?

Verse 23:32: And there were also two others, malefactors, led with him to be put to death.

Verse 23:33: And when they were come to the place, which is called Calvary, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, and the other on the left.

Verse 23:34:Jesus, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots Then said Jesus, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots.

Verse 23:35:He saved others; let him save himself, if he be Christ, the chosen of God And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also with them derided [him,] saying, He saved others; let him save himself, if he be Christ, the chosen of God.

Verse 23:36: And the soldiers also mocked him, coming to him, and offering him vinegar,

Verse 23:37: And saying, If thou be the king of the Jews, save thyself.

Verse 23:38: And a superscription also was written over him in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew, THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.

Verse 23:39: And one of the malefactors which were hanged railed on him, saying, If thou be Christ, save thyself and us.

Verse 23:40:Dost not thou fear God But the other answering rebuked him, saying, Dost not thou fear God, seeing thou art in the same condemnation?

Verse 23:41: And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing amiss.

Verse 23:42: And he said unto Jesus, Lord, remember me when thou comest into thy kingdom.

Verse 23:43:Verily I say unto thee, To day shalt thou be with me in paradise And Jesus said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, To day shalt thou be with me in paradise.

John

Verse 14:6:Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me.

Verse 14:7: If ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also: and from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him.

Verse 14:8: Philip saith unto him, Lord, shew us the Father, and it sufficeth us.

Verse 14:9: Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and yet hast thou not known me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; and how sayest thou [then,] Shew us the Father?

Verse 14:10: Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I speak unto you I speak not of myself: but the Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the works.

Verse 14:11:Believe me that I [am] in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works’ sake Believe me that I [am] in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works’ sake.

Philippians

Verse 2:5: Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:

Verse 2:6: Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God:

Verse 2:7:But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men:

Verse 2:8: And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.

Colossians

Verse 1:15:Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of every creature Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of every creature:

Verse 1:16:For by him were all things created and that are in earth, visible and invisible, whether [they be] thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him For by him were all things created , that are in heaven, and that are in earth, visible and invisible, whether [they be] thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him:

Verse 1:17:And he is before all things, and by him all things consist And he is before all things, and by him all things consist.

Verse 1:18: And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all [things] he might have the preeminence.

Verse 1:19: For it pleased [the Father] that in him should all fulness dwell;

Verse 1:20:having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself; by him, [I say,] And, having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself; by him, [I say,] whether [they be] things in earth, or things in heaven.

Luke

Verse 22:66: And as soon as it was day, the elders of the people and the chief priests and the scribes came together, and led him into their council, saying,

Verse 22:67: Art thou the Christ? tell us. And he said unto them, If I tell you, ye will not believe:

Verse 22:68: And if I also ask [you,] ye will not answer me, nor let [me] go.

Verse 22:69: Hereafter shall the Son of man sit on the right hand of the power of God.

Verse 22:70:Then said they all, Art thou then the Son of God? And he said unto them, Ye say that I am Then said they all, Art thou then the Son of God? And he said unto them, Ye say that I am.

Verse 22:71: And they said, What need we any further witness? for we ourselves have heard of his own mouth.

Parables

Matthew

Verse 13:10: And the disciples came, and said unto him, Why speakest thou unto them in parables?

Verse 13:11:Because it is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of but to them it is not given He answered and said unto them, Because it is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given.

Verse 13:12:For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that he hath For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that he hath.

Verse 13:13: Therefore speak I to them in parables: because they seeing see not; and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand.

Verse 13:14: And in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Esaias, which saith, By hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive:

Verse 13:15:For this people’s heart is waxed gross, and [their] ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have closed; lest at any time they should see with [their] eyes, and hear with [their] ears, and should understand with [their] heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them For this people’s heart is waxed gross, and [their] ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have closed; lest at any time they should see with [their] eyes, and hear with [their] ears, and should understand with [their] heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them.

Verse 13:16: But blessed [are] your eyes, for they see: and your ears, for they hear.

Revelations

Revelations

Verse 1:1:The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him, to shew unto his servants things which must shortly come to pass The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him, to shew unto his servants things which must shortly come to pass; and he sent and signified [it] by his angel unto his servant John:

Verse 1:2:Who bare record of the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ Who bare record of the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ, and of all things that he saw.

Verse 1:3: Blessed [is] he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this prophecy, and keep those things which are written therein: for the time [is] at hand.

Verse 1:4: John to the seven churches which are in Asia: Grace [be] unto you, and peace, from him which is, and which was, and which is to come; and from the seven Spirits which are before his throne;

Verse 1:5: And from Jesus Christ, [who is] the faithful witness, [and] the first begotten of the dead, and the prince of the kings of the earth. Unto him that loved us, and washed us from our sins in his own blood,

Verse 1:6: And hath made us kings and priests unto God and his Father; to him [be] glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.

Verse 1:7: Behold, he cometh with clouds; and every eye shall see him, and they [also] which pierced him: and all kindreds of the earth shall wail because of him. Even so, Amen.

Verse 1:8:I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, saith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Almighty I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, saith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Almighty.

Verse 1:9: I John, who also am your brother, and companion in tribulation, and in the kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ, was in the isle that is called Patmos, for the word of God, and for the testimony of Jesus Christ.

Verse 1:10: I was in the Spirit on the Lord’s day, and heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet,

Verse 1:11: What thou seest, write in a book, and send [it] unto the seven churches which are in Asia; unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamos, and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea Saying, I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last: and, What thou seest, write in a book, and send [it] unto the seven churches which are in Asia; unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamos, and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea.

Verse 1:12: And I turned to see the voice that spake with me. And being turned, I saw seven golden candlesticks;

Verse 1:13: And in the midst of the seven candlesticks [one] like unto the Son of man, clothed with a garment down to the foot, and girt about the paps with a golden girdle.

Verse 1:14: His head and [his] hairs [were] white like wool, as white as snow; and his eyes [were] as a flame of fire;

Verse 1:15: And his feet like unto fine brass, as if they burned in a furnace; and his voice as the sound of many waters.

Verse 1:16: And he had in his right hand seven stars: and out of his mouth went a sharp twoedged sword: and his countenance [was] as the sun shineth in his strength.

Verse 1:17:And when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead. And he laid his right hand upon me, saying unto me, Fear not; I am the first and the last And when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead. And he laid his right hand upon me, saying unto me, Fear not; I am the first and the last:

Verse 1:18:I [am] he that liveth, and was dead; and, behold, I am alive for evermore, Amen I [am] he that liveth, and was dead; and, behold, I am alive for evermore, Amen; and have the keys of hell and of death.

Verse 1:19: Write the things which thou hast seen, and the things which are, and the things which shall be hereafter;

Verse 1:20: The mystery of the seven stars which thou sawest in my right hand, and the seven golden candlesticks. The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches: and the seven candlesticks which thou sawest are the seven churches.

Verse 2:1: Unto the angel of the church of Ephesus write; These things saith he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, who walketh in the midst of the seven golden candlesticks;

Verse 2:2: I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canst not bear them which are evil: and thou hast tried them which say they are apostles, and are not, and hast found them liars:

Verse 2:3: And hast borne, and hast patience, and for my name’s sake hast laboured, and hast not fainted.

Verse 2:4:Nevertheless I have [somewhat] against thee, because thou hast left thy first love Nevertheless I have [somewhat] against thee, because thou hast left thy first love.

Verse 2:5: Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the first works; or else I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy candlestick out of his place, except thou repent.

Verse 2:6: But this thou hast, that thou hatest the deeds of the Nicolaitanes, which I also hate.

Verse 2:7: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life, which is in the midst of the paradise of God.

Verse 2:8: And unto the angel of the church in Smyrna write; These things saith the first and the last, which was dead, and is alive;

Verse 2:9: I know thy works, and tribulation, and poverty, (but thou art rich) and [I know] the blasphemy of them which say they are Jews, and are not, but [are] the synagogue of Satan.

Verse 2:10:Fear none of those things which thou shalt suffer Fear none of those things which thou shalt suffer: behold, the devil shall cast [some] of you into prison, that ye may be tried; and ye shall have tribulation ten days: be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life.

Verse 2:11: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; He that overcometh shall not be hurt of the second death.

Verse 2:12: And to the angel of the church in Pergamos write; These things saith he which hath the sharp sword with two edges;

Verse 2:13: I know thy works, and where thou dwellest, [even] where Satan’s seat [is:] and thou holdest fast my name, and hast not denied my faith, even in those days wherein Antipas [was] my faithful martyr, who was slain among you, where Satan dwelleth.

Verse 2:14: But I have a few things against thee, because thou hast there them that hold the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balac to cast a stumblingblock before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed unto idols, and to commit fornication.

Verse 2:15: So hast thou also them that hold the doctrine of the Nicolaitanes, which thing I hate.

Verse 2:16: Repent; or else I will come unto thee quickly, and will fight against them with the sword of my mouth.

Verse 2:17: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden manna, and will give him a white stone, and in the stone a new name written, which no man knoweth saving he that receiveth [it. ]

Verse 2:18:These things saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like unto a flame of fire, and his feet [are] like fine brass And unto the angel of the church in Thyatira write; These things saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like unto a flame of fire, and his feet [are] like fine brass;

Verse 2:19: I know thy works, and charity, and service, and faith, and thy patience, and thy works; and the last [to be] more than the first.

Verse 2:20: Notwithstanding I have a few things against thee, because thou sufferest that woman Jezebel, which calleth herself a prophetess, to teach and to seduce my servants to commit fornication, and to eat things sacrificed unto idols.

Verse 2:21: And I gave her space to repent of her fornication; and she repented not.

Verse 2:22: Behold, I will cast her into a bed, and them that commit adultery with her into great tribulation, except they repent of their deeds.

Verse 2:23: And I will kill her children with death; and all the churches shall know that I am he which searcheth the reins and hearts: and I will give unto every one of you according to your works.

Verse 2:24: But unto you I say, and unto the rest in Thyatira, as many as have not this doctrine, and which have not known the depths of Satan, as they speak; I will put upon you none other burden.

Verse 2:25: But that which ye have [already] hold fast till I come.

Verse 2:26: And he that overcometh, and keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give power over the nations:

Verse 2:27: And he shall rule them with a rod of iron; as the vessels of a potter shall they be broken to shivers: even as I received of my Father.

Verse 2:28: And I will give him the morning star.

Verse 2:29: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

Verse 3:1:These things saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars; I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and art dead And unto the angel of the church in Sardis write; These things saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars; I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and art dead.

Verse 3:2:Be watchful, and strengthen the things which remain, that are ready to die: for I have not found thy works perfect before God Be watchful, and strengthen the things which remain, that are ready to die: for I have not found thy works perfect before God.

Verse 3:3: Remember therefore how thou hast received and heard, and hold fast, and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come on thee as a thief, and thou shalt not know what hour I will come upon thee.

Verse 3:4: Thou hast a few names even in Sardis which have not defiled their garments; and they shall walk with me in white: for they are worthy.

Verse 3:5: He that overcometh, the same shall be clothed in white raiment; and I will not blot out his name out of the book of life, but I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels.

Verse 3:6: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

Verse 3:7: And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write; These things saith he that is holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of David, he that openeth, and no man shutteth; and shutteth, and no man openeth;

Verse 3:8: I know thy works: behold, I have set before thee an open door, and no man can shut it: for thou hast a little strength, and hast kept my word, and hast not denied my name.

Verse 3:9: Behold, I will make them of the synagogue of Satan, which say they are Jews, and are not, but do lie; behold, I will make them to come and worship before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee.

Verse 3:10: Because thou hast kept the word of my patience, I also will keep thee from the hour of temptation, which shall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth.

Verse 3:11: Behold, I come quickly: hold that fast which thou hast, that no man take thy crown.

Verse 3:12:Him that overcometh will I make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go no more out: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, [which is] new Jerusalem, which cometh down out offrom my God: and [I will write upon him] my new name Him that overcometh will I make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go no more out: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, [which is] new Jerusalem, which cometh down out of heaven from my God: and [I will write upon him] my new name.

Verse 3:13: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

Verse 3:14:These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God And unto the angel of the church of the Laodiceans write; These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God;

Verse 3:15: I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wert cold or hot.

Verse 3:16: So then because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth.

Verse 3:17: Because thou sayest, I am rich, and increased with goods, and have need of nothing; and knowest not that thou art wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked:

Verse 3:18: I counsel thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou mayest be rich; and white raiment, that thou mayest be clothed, and [that] the shame of thy nakedness do not appear; and anoint thine eyes with eyesalve, that thou mayest see.

Verse 3:19: As many as I love, I rebuke and chasten: be zealous therefore, and repent.

Verse 3:20: Behold, I stand at the door, and knock: if any man hear my voice, and open the door, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he with me.

Verse 3:21: To him that overcometh will I grant to sit with me in my throne, even as I also overcame, and am set down with my Father in his throne.

Verse 3:22: He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

Revelations

Verse 8:1: And when he had opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven about the space of half an hour.

Verse 8:2:And I saw the seven angels which stood before God And I saw the seven angels which stood before God; and to them were given seven trumpets.

Verse 8:3: And another angel came and stood at the altar, having a golden censer; and there was given unto him much incense, that he should offer [it] with the prayers of all saints upon the golden altar which was before the throne.

Verse 8:4:And the smoke of the incense, [which came] with the prayers of the saints, ascended up before God And the smoke of the incense, [which came] with the prayers of the saints, ascended up before God out of the angel’s hand.

Verse 8:5: And the angel took the censer, and filled it with fire of the altar, and cast [it] into the earth: and there were voices, and thunderings, and lightnings, and an earthquake.

Verse 8:6: And the seven angels which had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound.

Verse 8:7: The first angel sounded, and there followed hail and fire mingled with blood, and they were cast upon the earth: and the third part of trees was burnt up, and all green grass was burnt up.

Verse 8:8: And the second angel sounded, and as it were a great mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea: and the third part of the sea became blood;

Verse 8:9: And the third part of the creatures which were in the sea, and had life, died; and the third part of the ships were destroyed.

Verse 8:10: And the third angel sounded, and there fell a great star from heaven, burning as it were a lamp, and it fell upon the third part of the rivers, and upon the fountains of waters;

Verse 8:11:And the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter And the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter.

Verse 8:12: And the fourth angel sounded, and the third part of the sun was smitten, and the third part of the moon, and the third part of the stars; so as the third part of them was darkened, and the day shone not for a third part of it, and the night likewise.

Verse 8:13:Woe, woe, woe, to the inhabiters of the earth by reason of the other voices of the trumpet of the three angels, which are yet to sound And I beheld, and heard an angel flying through the midst of heaven, saying with a loud voice, Woe, woe, woe, to the inhabiters of the earth by reason of the other voices of the trumpet of the three angels, which are yet to sound!

Verse 9:1: And the fifth angel sounded, and I saw a star fall from heaven unto the earth: and to him was given the key of the bottomless pit.

Verse 9:2: And he opened the bottomless pit; and there arose a smoke out of the pit, as the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the air were darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit.

Verse 9:3: And there came out of the smoke locusts upon the earth: and unto them was given power, as the scorpions of the earth have power.

Verse 9:4:And it was commanded them that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree; but only those men which have not the seal of God in their foreheads And it was commanded them that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree; but only those men which have not the seal of God in their foreheads.

Verse 9:5:And to them it was given that they should not kill them, but that they should be tormented five months: and their torment [was] as the torment of a scorpion, when he striketh a man And to them it was given that they should not kill them, but that they should be tormented five months: and their torment [was] as the torment of a scorpion, when he striketh a man.

Verse 9:6:And in those days shall men seek death, and shall not find it; and shall desire to die, and death shall flee from them And in those days shall men seek death, and shall not find it; and shall desire to die, and death shall flee from them.

Verse 9:7: And the shapes of the locusts [were] like unto horses prepared unto battle; and on their heads [were] as it were crowns like gold, and their faces [were] as the faces of men.

Verse 9:8: And they had hair as the hair of women, and their teeth were as [the teeth] of lions.

Verse 9:9: And they had breastplates, as it were breastplates of iron; and the sound of their wings [was] as the sound of chariots of many horses running to battle.

Verse 9:10: And they had tails like unto scorpions, and there were stings in their tails: and their power [was] to hurt men five months.

Verse 9:11: And they had a king over them, [which is] the angel of the bottomless pit, whose name in the Hebrew tongue [is] Abaddon, but in the Greek tongue hath [his] name Apollyon.

Verse 9:12:One woe is past; [and,] behold, there come two woes more hereafter One woe is past; [and,] behold, there come two woes more hereafter.

Verse 9:13:I heard a voice from the four horns of the golden altar which is before God And the sixth angel sounded, and I heard a voice from the four horns of the golden altar which is before God,

Verse 9:14: Saying to the sixth angel which had the trumpet, Loose the four angels which are bound in the great river Euphrates.

Verse 9:15:And the four angels were loosed, which were prepared for an hour, and a day, and a month, and a year, for to slay the third part of men And the four angels were loosed, which were prepared for an hour, and a day, and a month, and a year, for to slay the third part of men.

Verse 9:16: And the number of the army of the horsemen [were] two hundred thousand thousand: and I heard the number of them.

Verse 9:17: And thus I saw the horses in the vision, and them that sat on them, having breastplates of fire, and of jacinth, and brimstone: and the heads of the horses [were] as the heads of lions; and out of their mouths issued fire and smoke and brimstone.

Verse 9:18:By these three was the third part of men killed, by the fire, and by the smoke, and by the brimstone, which issued out of their mouths By these three was the third part of men killed, by the fire, and by the smoke, and by the brimstone, which issued out of their mouths.

Verse 9:19: For their power is in their mouth, and in their tails: for their tails [were] like unto serpents, and had heads, and with them they do hurt.

Verse 9:20: And the rest of the men which were not killed by these plagues yet repented not of the works of their hands, that they should not worship devils, and idols of gold, and silver, and brass, and stone, and of wood: which neither can see, nor hear, nor walk:

Verse 9:21: Neither repented they of their murders, nor of their sorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of their thefts.

Verse 10:1: And I saw another mighty angel come down from heaven, clothed with a cloud: and a rainbow [was] upon his head, and his face [was] as it were the sun, and his feet as pillars of fire:

Verse 10:2: And he had in his hand a little book open: and he set his right foot upon the sea, and [his] left [foot] on the earth,

Verse 10:3: And cried with a loud voice, as [when] a lion roareth: and when he had cried, seven thunders uttered their voices.

Verse 10:4: And when the seven thunders had uttered their voices, I was about to write: and I heard a voice from heaven saying unto me, Seal up those things which the seven thunders uttered, and write them not.

Verse 10:5: And the angel which I saw stand upon the sea and upon the earth lifted up his hand to heaven,

Verse 10:6:And sware by him that liveth for ever and ever, who createdand the things that therein are, and the earth, and the things that therein are, and the sea, and the things which are therein, that there should be time no longer And sware by him that liveth for ever and ever, who created heaven, and the things that therein are, and the earth, and the things that therein are, and the sea, and the things which are therein, that there should be time no longer:

Verse 10:7:the mystery of God should be finished, as he hath declared to his servants the prophets But in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he shall begin to sound, the mystery of God should be finished, as he hath declared to his servants the prophets.

Verse 10:8: And the voice which I heard from heaven spake unto me again, and said, Go [and] take the little book which is open in the hand of the angel which standeth upon the sea and upon the earth.

Verse 10:9: And I went unto the angel, and said unto him, Give me the little book. And he said unto me, Take [it,] and eat it up; and it shall make thy belly bitter, but it shall be in thy mouth sweet as honey.

Verse 10:10: And I took the little book out of the angel’s hand, and ate it up; and it was in my mouth sweet as honey: and as soon as I had eaten it, my belly was bitter.

Verse 10:11: And he said unto me, Thou must prophesy again before many peoples, and nations, and tongues, and kings.

Verse 11:1: And there was given me a reed like unto a rod: and the angel stood, saying, Rise, and measure the temple of God, and the altar, and them that worship therein.

Verse 11:2: But the court which is without the temple leave out, and measure it not; for it is given unto the Gentiles: and the holy city shall they tread under foot forty [and] two months.

Verse 11:3:And I will give [power] unto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred [and] threescore days, clothed in sackcloth And I will give [power] unto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred [and] threescore days, clothed in sackcloth.

Verse 11:4:two olive trees, and the two candlesticks standing before the God of the earth These are the two olive trees, and the two candlesticks standing before the God of the earth.

Verse 11:5:And if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, he must in this manner be killed And if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, he must in this manner be killed.

Verse 11:6: These have power to shut heaven, that it rain not in the days of their prophecy: and have power over waters to turn them to blood, and to smite the earth with all plagues, as often as they will.

Verse 11:7:And when they shall have finished their testimony, the beast that ascendeth out of the bottomless pit shall make war against them, and shall overcome them, and kill them And when they shall have finished their testimony, the beast that ascendeth out of the bottomless pit shall make war against them, and shall overcome them, and kill them.

Verse 11:8:And their dead bodies [shall lie] in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also our Lord was crucified And their dead bodies [shall lie] in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also our Lord was crucified.

Verse 11:9: And they of the people and kindreds and tongues and nations shall see their dead bodies three days and an half, and shall not suffer their dead bodies to be put in graves.

Verse 11:10: And they that dwell upon the earth shall rejoice over them, and make merry, and shall send gifts one to another; because these two prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.

Verse 11:11:And after three days and an half the Spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feetgreat fear fell upon them which saw them And after three days and an half the Spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feet; and great fear fell upon them which saw them.

Verse 11:12: And they heard a great voice from heaven saying unto them, Come up hither. And they ascended up to heaven in a cloud; and their enemies beheld them.

Verse 11:13:And the same hour was there a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city fell, and in the earthquake were slain of men seven thousand: and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of And the same hour was there a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city fell, and in the earthquake were slain of men seven thousand: and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of heaven.

Verse 11:14: The second woe is past; [and,] behold, the third woe cometh quickly.

Verse 11:15:The kingdoms of this world are become [the kingdoms] of our Lord, and of his Christ; and he shall reign for ever and ever And the seventh angel sounded; and there were great voices in heaven, saying, The kingdoms of this world are become [the kingdoms] of our Lord, and of his Christ; and he shall reign for ever and ever.

Verse 11:16: And the four and twenty elders, which sat before God on their seats, fell upon their faces, and worshipped God ,

Verse 11:17: Saying, We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art, and wast, and art to come; because thou hast taken to thee thy great power, and hast reigned.

Verse 11:18:them that fear thy name And the nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead, that they should be judged, and that thou shouldest give reward unto thy servants the prophets, and to the saints, and them that fear thy name, small and great; and shouldest destroy them which destroy the earth.

Verse 11:19:And the temple of God was opened in and there was seen in his temple the ark of his testament: and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunderings, and an earthquake, and great hail And the temple of God was opened in heaven, and there was seen in his temple the ark of his testament: and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunderings, and an earthquake, and great hail.

Revelations

Verse 21:1: And I saw a new heaven and a new earth: for the first heaven and the first earth were passed away; and there was no more sea.

Verse 21:2:And I John saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of And I John saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.

Verse 21:3:Behold, the tabernacle of God [is] with men, and he will dwell with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself shall be with them, [and be] their God And I heard a great voice out of heaven saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God [is] with men, and he will dwell with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself shall be with them, [and be] their God.

Verse 21:4:And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there shall be no more death, neither sorrow, nor crying, neither shall there be any more pain: for the former things are passed away And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there shall be no more death, neither sorrow, nor crying, neither shall there be any more pain: for the former things are passed away.

Verse 21:5:Behold, I make all things new. And he said unto me, Write: for these words are true and faithful And he that sat upon the throne said, Behold, I make all things new. And he said unto me, Write: for these words are true and faithful.

Verse 21:6: I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely And he said unto me, It is done. I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely.

Verse 21:7:He that overcometh shall inherit all things; and I will be his God, and he shall be my son He that overcometh shall inherit all things; and I will be his God, and he shall be my son.

Verse 21:8:But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death.

Verse 21:9: And there came unto me one of the seven angels which had the seven vials full of the seven last plagues, and talked with me, saying, Come hither, I will shew thee the bride, the Lamb’s wife.

Verse 21:10:shewed me that great city, the holy Jerusalem, descending out of from God And he carried me away in the spirit to a great and high mountain, and shewed me that great city, the holy Jerusalem, descending out of heaven from God,

Verse 21:11:Having the glory of God: and her light [was] like unto a stone most precious, even like a jasper stone, clear as crystal Having the glory of God: and her light [was] like unto a stone most precious, even like a jasper stone, clear as crystal;

Verse 21:12: And had a wall great and high, [and] had twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, and names written thereon, which are [the names] of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel:

Verse 21:13: On the east three gates; on the north three gates; on the south three gates; and on the west three gates.

Verse 21:14: And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and in them the names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb.

Verse 21:15: And he that talked with me had a golden reed to measure the city, and the gates thereof, and the wall thereof.

Verse 21:16: And the city lieth foursquare, and the length is as large as the breadth: and he measured the city with the reed, twelve thousand furlongs. The length and the breadth and the height of it are equal.

Verse 21:17: And he measured the wall thereof, an hundred [and] forty [and] four cubits, [according to] the measure of a man, that is, of the angel.

Verse 21:18: And the building of the wall of it was [of] jasper: and the city [was] pure gold, like unto clear glass.

Verse 21:19: And the foundations of the wall of the city [were] garnished with all manner of precious stones. The first foundation [was] jasper; the second, sapphire; the third, a chalcedony; the fourth, an emerald;

Verse 21:20: The fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardius; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, a topaz; the tenth, a chrysoprasus; the eleventh, a jacinth; the twelfth, an amethyst.

Verse 21:21: And the twelve gates [were] twelve pearls; every several gate was of one pearl: and the street of the city [was] pure gold, as it were transparent glass.

Verse 21:22:And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple of it And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple of it.

Verse 21:23:And the city had no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb [is] the light thereof And the city had no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb [is] the light thereof.

Verse 21:24: And the nations of them which are saved shall walk in the light of it: and the kings of the earth do bring their glory and honour into it.

Verse 21:25: And the gates of it shall not be shut at all by day: for there shall be no night there.

Verse 21:26:And they shall bring the glory and honour of the nations into it And they shall bring the glory and honour of the nations into it.

Verse 21:27: And there shall in no wise enter into it any thing that defileth, neither [whatsoever] worketh abomination, or [maketh] a lie: but they which are written in the Lamb’s book of life.

Verse 22:1:And he shewed me a pure river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb And he shewed me a pure river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb.

Verse 22:2: In the midst of the street of it, and on either side of the river, [was there] the tree of life, which bare twelve [manner] of fruits, [and] yielded her fruit every month: and the leaves of the tree [were] for the healing of the nations.

Verse 22:3: And there shall be no more curse: but the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it; and his servants shall serve him:

Verse 22:4: And they shall see his face; and his name [shall be] in their foreheads.

Verse 22:5:for the Lord God giveth them light And there shall be no night there; and they need no candle, neither light of the sun; for the Lord God giveth them light: and they shall reign for ever and ever.

Verse 22:6: And he said unto me, These sayings [are] faithful and true: and the Lord God of the holy prophets sent his angel to shew unto his servants the things which must shortly be done.

Verse 22:7: Behold, I come quickly: blessed is he that keepeth the sayings of the prophecy of this book.

Verse 22:8: And I John saw these things, and heard [them.] And when I had heard and seen, I fell down to worship before the feet of the angel which shewed me these things.

Verse 22:9: Then saith he unto me, See [thou do it] not: for I am thy fellowservant, and of thy brethren the prophets, and of them which keep the sayings of this book: worship God.

Verse 22:10: And he saith unto me, Seal not the sayings of the prophecy of this book: for the time is at hand.

Verse 22:11:He that is unjust, let him be unjust still: and he which is filthy, let him be filthy still: and he that is righteous, let him be righteous still: and he that is holy, let him be holy still He that is unjust, let him be unjust still: and he which is filthy, let him be filthy still: and he that is righteous, let him be righteous still: and he that is holy, let him be holy still.

Verse 22:12: And, behold, I come quickly; and my reward [is] with me, to give every man according as his work shall be.

Verse 22:13:I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and the last I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and the last.

Verse 22:14: Blessed [are] they that do his commandments, that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the city.

Verse 22:15:For without [are] dogs, and sorcerers, and whoremongers, and murderers, and idolaters, and whosoever loveth and maketh a lie For without [are] dogs, and sorcerers, and whoremongers, and murderers, and idolaters, and whosoever loveth and maketh a lie.

Verse 22:16:I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify unto you these things in the churches. I am the root and the offspring of David, [and] the bright and morning star I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify unto you these things in the churches. I am the root and the offspring of David, [and] the bright and morning star.

Verse 22:17:And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come. And let him that is athirst come. And whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come. And let him that is athirst come. And whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely.

Verse 22:18:For I testify unto every man that heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, If any man shall add unto these things, God shall add unto him the plagues that are written in this book For I testify unto every man that heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, If any man shall add unto these things, God shall add unto him the plagues that are written in this book:

Verse 22:19:And if any man shall take away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part out of the book of life, and out of the holy city, and [from] the things which are written in this book And if any man shall take away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part out of the book of life, and out of the holy city, and [from] the things which are written in this book.

Verse 22:20: He which testifieth these things saith, Surely I come quickly. Amen. Even so, come, Lord Jesus.

Abraham

Hebrews

Verse 11:8: By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which he should after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out, not knowing whither he went.

Verse 11:9: By faith he sojourned in the land of promise, as [in] a strange country, dwelling in tabernacles with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise:

Verse 11:10:For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker [is] God For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker [is] God.

James

Verse 2:21: Was not Abraham our father justified by works, when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar?

Creation

Chapter 14

God is He Who created the heavens and the earth, and sends down water from the sky, and with it produces fruits for your sustenance. And He committed the ships to your service, sailing through the sea by His command, and He committed the rivers to your service.

And He committed the sun and the moon to your service, both continuously pursuing their courses, and He committed the night and the day to your service.

And He has given you something of all what you asked. And if you were to count God’s blessings, you would not be able to enumerate them. The human being is unfair and ungrateful.

Chapter 23

We created man from an extract of clay.

Then We made him a seed, in a secure repository.

Then We developed the seed into a clot. Then We developed the clot into a lump. Then We developed the lump into bones. Then We clothed the bones with flesh. Then We produced it into another creature. Most Blessed is God, the Best of Creators.

Chapter 35

Praise be to God, Originator of the heavens and the earth, Maker of the angels messengers with wings—double, triple, and quadruple. He adds to creation as He wills. God is Able to do all things.

Chapter 39

God is the Creator of all things, and He is in Charge of all things.

Home
Methods
Background
Texts
Results

Texts

Stories / Characters

Abraham Creation Jesus Moses Noah Parables The End Times

Text

Torah New Testament Quran

Labels

God as the Creator God as Wrathful God as Loving God as Powerful God as Merciful God as Other (positive) God as Other (negative) God as Other (neutral) Fear of God Love Recipient is God Other recipient Respect Recipient is God Other recipient Worship Recipient is God Other recipient Blessings Heaven Hell

Torah

Creation

Genesis

1:1

In the beginning

God created the heaven and the earth.

1:2

And the earth was without form, and void; and darkness [was] upon the face of the deep. And the Spirit of

God moved upon the face of the waters.

1:3

And

God said, Let there be light: and there was light.

1:4

And

God saw the light, that [it was] good: and God divided the light from the darkness.

1:5

And

God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. And the evening and the morning were the first day.

1:6

And

God said, Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters.

1:7

And

God made the firmament, and divided the waters which [were] under the firmament from the waters which [were] above the firmament: and it was so.

1:8

And

God

called the firmament

Heaven

. And the evening and the morning were the second day.

1:9

And

God said, Let the waters under the heaven be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry [land] appear: and it was so.

1:10

And

God called the dry [land] Earth; and the gathering together of the waters called he Seas: and God saw that [it was] good.

1:11

And

God said, Let the earth bring forth grass, the herb yielding seed, [and] the fruit tree yielding fruit after his kind, whose seed [is] in itself, upon the earth: and it was so.

1:12

And the earth brought forth grass, [and] herb yielding seed after his kind, and the tree yielding fruit, whose seed [was] in itself, after his kind: and

God

saw that [it was] good.

1:13

And the evening and the morning were the third day.

1:14

And

God said, Let there be lights in the firmament of the heaven to divide the day from the night; and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days, and years:

1:15

And let them be for lights in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth: and it was so.

1:16

And

God made two great lights; the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night: [he made] the stars also.

1:17

And

God set them in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth,

1:18

And to rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkness: and God saw that [it was] good.

1:19

And the evening and the morning were the fourth day.

1:20

And

God said, Let the waters bring forth abundantly the moving creature that hath life, and fowl [that] may fly above the earth in the open firmament of heaven.

1:21

And

Godcreated great whales, and every living creature that moveth, which the waters brought forth abundantly, after their kind, and every winged fowl after his kind:

and God saw that [it was] good.

1:22

And

God

blessed them, saying,

Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let fowl multiply in the earth.

1:23

And the evening and the morning were the fifth day.

1:24

And

God said, Let the earth bring forth the living creature after his kind, cattle, and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after his kind: and it was so.

1:25

And

God made the beast of the earth after his kind, and cattle after their kind, and every thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind: and God saw that [it was] good.

1:26

And

God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.

1:27

So

God created man in his [own] image, in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them.

1:28

And

God blessed them

, and

God said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it: and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the earth.

1:29

And

God said, Behold, I have given you every herb bearing seed, which [is] upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in the which [is] the fruit of a tree yielding seed; to you it shall be for meat.

1:30

And to every beast of the earth, and to every fowl of the air, and to every thing that creepeth upon the earth, wherein [there is] life, [I have given] every green herb for meat: and it was so.

1:31

And

God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, [it was] very good.

And the evening and the morning were the sixth day.

2:1

Thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them.

2:2

And on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made.

2:3

And

God

blessed

the seventh day, and sanctified it:

because that in it he had rested from all his work which God created and made.

Noah and the Flood (Genesis 6:1-9:19)

Genesis

6:1

And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth, and daughters were born unto them,

6:2

That the sons of God saw the daughters of men that they [were] fair; and they took them wives of all which they chose.

6:3

And

the LORD said, My spirit shall not always strive with man, for that he also [is] flesh: yet his days shall be an hundred and twenty years.

6:4

There were giants in the earth in those days; and also after that, when the sons of God came in unto the daughters of men, and they bare [children] to them, the same [became] mighty men which [were] of old, men of renown.

6:5

And

GOD saw that the wickedness of man [was] great in the earth, and [that] every imagination of the thoughts of his heart [was] only evil continually.

6:6

And it

repented the LORD that he had made man on the earth

, and it grieved him at his heart.

6:7

And the

LORD said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth; both man, and beast, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air; for it repenteth me that I have made them.

6:8

But Noah found grace in the eyes of the LORD.

6:9

These [are] the generations of Noah: Noah was a just man [and] perfect in his generations, [and]

Noah walked with God

.

6:10

And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

6:11

The earth also was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence.

6:12

And

God looked upon the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt;

for all flesh had corrupted his way upon the earth.

6:13

And

God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me; for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them with the earth.

6:14

Make thee an ark of gopher wood; rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch.

6:15

And this [is the fashion] which thou shalt make it [of:] The length of the ark [shall be] three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits.

6:16

A window shalt thou make to the ark, and in a cubit shalt thou finish it above; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; [with] lower, second, and third [stories] shalt thou make it.

6:17

And, behold, I

, even I, do bring a flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein [is] the breath of life, from under heaven; [and] every thing that [is] in the earth shall die.

6:18

But with thee will I establish my covenant

; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy sons’ wives with thee.

6:19

And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every [sort] shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep [them] alive with thee; they shall be male and female.

6:20

Of fowls after their kind, and of cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the earth after his kind, two of every [sort] shall come unto thee, to keep [them] alive.

6:21

And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and thou shalt gather [it] to thee; and it shall be for food for thee, and for them.

6:22

Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.

7:1

And the LORD said unto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation.

7:2

Of every clean beast thou shalt take to thee by sevens, the male and his female: and of beasts that [are] not clean by two, the male and his female.

7:3

Of fowls also of the air by sevens, the male and the female; to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth.

7:4

For yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and

every living substance that I have made will I destroy from off the face of the earth.

7:5

And Noah did according unto all that the LORD commanded him.

7:6

And Noah [was] six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth.

7:7

And Noah went in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him, into the ark, because of the waters of the flood.

7:8

Of clean beasts, and of beasts that [are] not clean, and of fowls, and of every thing that creepeth upon the earth,

7:9

There went in two and two unto Noah into the ark, the male and the female, as God had commanded Noah.

7:10

And it came to pass after seven days, that the waters of the flood were upon the earth.

7:11

In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life, in the second month, the seventeenth day of the month, the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened.

7:12

And the rain was upon the earth forty days and forty nights.

7:13

In the selfsame day entered Noah, and Shem, and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah’s wife, and the three wives of his sons with them, into the ark;

7:14

They, and every beast after his kind, and all the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind, and every fowl after his kind, every bird of every sort.

7:15

And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two and two of all flesh, wherein [is] the breath of life.

7:16

And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God had commanded him:

and the LORD shut him in.

7:17

And the flood was forty days upon the earth; and the waters increased, and bare up the ark, and it was lift up above the earth.

7:18

And the waters prevailed, and were increased greatly upon the earth; and the ark went upon the face of the waters.

7:19

And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth; and all the high hills, that [were] under the whole heaven, were covered.

7:20

Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail; and the mountains were covered.

7:21

And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both of fowl, and of cattle, and of beast, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth, and every man:

7:22

All in whose nostrils [was] the breath of life, of all that [was] in the dry [land,] died.

7:23

And every living substance was destroyed which was upon the face of the ground, both man, and cattle, and the creeping things, and the fowl of the heaven; and they were destroyed from the earth: and Noah only remained [alive,] and they that [were] with him in the ark.

7:24

And the waters prevailed upon the earth an hundred and fifty days.

8:1

And God remembered Noah, and every living thing, and all the cattle that [was] with him in the ark: and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters asswaged;

8:2

The fountains also of the deep and the windows ofheaven were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained;

8:3

And the waters returned from off the earth continually: and after the end of the hundred and fifty days the waters were abated.

8:4

And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat.

8:5

And the waters decreased continually until the tenth month: in the tenth [month,] on the first [day] of the month, were the tops of the mountains seen.

8:6

And it came to pass at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made:

8:7

And he sent forth a raven, which went forth to and fro, until the waters were dried up from off the earth.

8:8

Also he sent forth a dove from him, to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground;

8:9

But the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him into the ark, for the waters [were] on the face of the whole earth: then he put forth his hand, and took her, and pulled her in unto him into the ark.

8:10

And he stayed yet other seven days; and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark;

8:11

And the dove came in to him in the evening; and, lo, in her mouth [was] an olive leaf pluckt off: so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth.

8:12

And he stayed yet other seven days; and sent forth the dove; which returned not again unto him any more.

8:13

And it came to pass in the six hundredth and first year, in the first [month,] the first [day] of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth: and Noah removed the covering of the ark, and looked, and, behold, the face of the ground was dry.

8:14

And in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, was the earth dried.

8:15

And God spake unto Noah

, saying,

8:16

Go forth of the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons’ wives with thee.

8:17

Bring forth with thee every living thing that [is] with thee, of all flesh, [both] of fowl, and of cattle, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth; that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth.

8:18

And Noah went forth, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him:

8:19

Every beast, everycreeping thing, and every fowl, [and] whatsoever creepeth upon the earth, after their kinds, went forth out of the ark.

8:20

And Noah builded an altar unto the LORD;

and took of every clean beast, and of every clean fowl, and offered burnt offerings on the altar.

8:21

And the

LORD smelled a sweet savour;and the LORD said in his heart

,

I will not again curse the ground any more for man’s sake; for the imagination of man’s heart [is] evil from his youth; neither will I again smite any more every thing living, as I have done.

8:22

While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.

9:1

And

God blessed Noah and his sons

, and said unto them,

Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth.

9:2

And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every fowl of the air, upon all that moveth [upon] the earth, and upon all the fishes of the sea; into your hand are they delivered.

9:3

Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you; even as the green herb have I given you all things.

9:4

But flesh with the life thereof, [which is] the blood thereof, shall ye not eat.

9:5

And surely your blood of your lives will I require; at the hand of every beast will I require it, and at the hand of man; at the hand of every man’s brother will I require the life of man.

9:6

Whoso sheddeth man’s blood, by man shall his blood be shed: for in the image of God made he man.

9:7

And you, be ye fruitful, and multiply; bring forth abundantly in the earth, and multiply therein.

9:8

And

God spake unto Noah

, and to his sons with him, saying,

9:9

And I, behold, I establish my covenant with you, and with your seed after you;

9:10

And with every living creature that [is] with you, of the fowl, of the cattle, and of every beast of the earth with you; from all that go out of the ark, to every beast of the earth.

9:11

And I will establish my covenant with you;

neither shall all flesh be cut off any more by the waters of a flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth.

9:12

And

God said, This [is] the token of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living creature that [is] with you,for perpetual generations:

9:13

Ido set my bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth.

9:14

And it shall come to pass, when

I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen in the cloud:

9:15

And

I will remember my covenant

, which [is] between me and you and every living creature of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh.

9:16

And the bow shall be in the cloud; and

I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting covenant

between God and every living creature of all flesh that [is] upon the earth.

9:17

And

God said unto Noah, This [is] the token of the covenant, which I have established between me and all flesh that [is] upon the earth.

9:18

And the sons of Noah, that went forth of the ark, were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth: and Ham is the father of Canaan.

9:19

These [are] the three sons of Noah: and of them was the whole earth overspread.

Moses

Exodus

2:1

And there went a man of the house of Levi, and took [to wife] a daughter of Levi.

2:2

And the woman conceived, and bare a son: and when she saw him that he [was a] goodly [child,] she hid him three months.

2:3

And when she could not longer hide him, she took for him an ark of bulrushes, and daubed it with slime and withpitch, and put the child therein; and she laid [it] in the flags by the river’s brink.

2:4

And his sister stood afar off, to wit what would be done to him.

2:5

And the daughter of Pharaoh came down to wash [herself] at the river; and her maidens walked along by the river’s side; and when she saw the ark among the flags, she sent her maid to fetch it.

2:6

And when she had opened [it,] she saw the child: and, behold, the babe wept. And she had compassion on him, and said, This [is one] of the Hebrews’ children.

2:7

Then said his sister to Pharaoh’s daughter, Shall I go and call to thee a nurse of the Hebrew women, that she may nurse the child for thee?

2:8

And Pharaoh’s daughter said to her, Go. And the maid went and called the child’s mother.

2:9

And Pharaoh’s daughter said unto her, Take this child away, and nurse it for me, and I will give [thee] thy wages. And the woman took the child, and nursed it.

2:10

And the child grew, and she brought him unto Pharaoh’s daughter, and he became her son. And she called his name Moses: and she said, Because I drew him out of the water.

2:11

And it came to pass in those days, when Moses was grown, that he went out unto his brethren, and looked on their burdens: and he spied an Egyptian smiting an Hebrew, one of his brethren.

2:12

And he looked this way and that way, and when he saw that [there was] no man, he slew the Egyptian, and hid him in the sand.

2:13

And when he went out the second day, behold, two men of the Hebrews strove together: and he said to him that did the wrong, Wherefore smitest thou thy fellow?

2:14

And he said, Who made thee a prince and a judge over us? intendest thou to kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian? And Moses feared, and said, Surely this thing is known.

2:15

Now when Pharaoh heard this thing, he sought to slay Moses. But Moses fled from the face of Pharaoh, and dwelt in the land of Midian: and he sat down by a well.

2:16

Now the priest of Midian had seven daughters: and they came and drew [water,] and filled the troughs to water their father’s flock.

2:17

And the shepherds came and drove them away: but Moses stood up and helped them, and watered their flock.

2:18

And when they came to Reuel their father, he said, How [is it that] ye are come so soon to day?

2:19

And they said, An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and also drew [water] enough for us, and watered the flock.

2:20

And he said unto his daughters, And where [is] he? why [is] it [that] ye have left the man? call him, that he may eat bread.

2:21

And Moses was content to dwell with the man: and he gave Moses Zipporah his daughter.

2:22

And she bare [him] a son, and he called his name Gershom: for he said, I have been a stranger in a strange land.

2:23

And it came to pass in process of time, that the king of Egypt died: and the children of Israel sighed by reason of the bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto God by reason of the bondage.

2:24

And

God heard their groaning, and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob.

2:25

And

God looked upon the children of Israel,

and God had

respect

unto [them.]

Exodus 3:1-6

Exodus

3:1

Now Moses kept the flock of Jethro his father in law, the priest of Midian: and he led the flock to the backside of the desert, and came to the mountain of God, [even] to Horeb.

3:2

And the angel of the LORD appeared unto him in a flame of fire out of the midst of a bush: and he looked, and, behold, the bush burned with fire, and the bush [was] not consumed.

3:3

And Moses said, I will now turn aside, and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt.

3:4

And when the LORD saw that he turned aside to see,

God called unto him out of the midst of the bush, and said, Moses, Moses. And he said, Here [am] I.

3:5

And he said, Draw not nigh hither: put off thy shoes from off thy feet, for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground.

3:6

Moreover he said, I [am] the God of thy father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.

And Moses hid his face; for he was afraid to look upon God

.

Exodus

18:1

When Jethro, the priest of Midian, Moses’ father in law,

heard of all that God had done for Moses,

and for Israel his people, [and] that the LORD had brought Israel out of Egypt;

18:2

Then Jethro, Moses’ father in law, took Zipporah, Moses’ wife, after he had sent her back,

18:3

And her two sons; of whichthe name of the one [was] Gershom; for he said, I have been an alien in a strange land:

18:4

And the name of the other [was] Eliezer; for the God of my father, [said he, was] mine help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh:

18:5

And Jethro, Moses’ father in law, came with his sons and his wife unto Moses into the wilderness, where he encamped at the mount of God:

18:6

And he said unto Moses, I thy father in law Jethro am come unto thee, and thy wife, and her two sons with her.

18:7

And Moses went out to meet his father in law, and did obeisance, and kissed him; and they asked each other of [their] welfare; and they came into the tent.

18:8

And Moses told his father in law all that the

LORD had done unto Pharaoh and to the Egyptians for Israel’s sake, [and] all the travail that had come upon them by the way, and [how] the LORD delivered them.

18:9

And Jethro rejoiced for all the goodness which the LORD had done to Israel, whom he had delivered out of the hand of the Egyptians.

18:10

And Jethro said,

Blessed [be] the LORD, who hath delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians,

and out of the hand of Pharaoh, who hath delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians.

18:11

Now I know that the

LORD [is] greater than all gods: for in the thing wherein they dealt proudly [he was] above them.

18:12

And Jethro, Moses’ father in law,

took a burnt offering and sacrifices for God:

and Aaron came, and all the elders of Israel, to eat bread with Moses’ father in law before God.

18:13

And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses sat to judge the people: and the people stood by Moses from the morning unto the evening.

18:14

And when Moses’ father in law saw all that he did to the people, he said, What [is] this thing that thou doest to the people? why sittest thou thyself alone, and all the people stand by thee from morning unto even?

18:15

And Moses said unto his father in law, Because the people come unto me to enquire of God:

18:16

When they have a matter, they come unto me; and I judge between one and another, and I do make [them] know the statutes of God, and his laws.

18:17

And Moses’ father in law said unto him, The thing that thou doest [is] not good.

18:18

Thou wilt surely wear away, both thou, and this people that [is] with thee: for this thing [is] too heavy for thee; thou art not able to perform it thyself alone.

18:19

Hearken now unto my voice, I will give thee counsel, and

God shall be with thee:

Be thou for the people to God-ward, that thou mayest bring the causes unto God:

18:20

And thou shalt teach them ordinances and laws, and shalt shew them the way wherein they must walk, and the work that they must do.

18:21

Moreover thou shalt provide out of

all the people able men, such as fear God, men of truth,

hating covetousness; and place [such] over them, [to be] rulers of thousands, [and] rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens:

18:22

And let them judge the people at all seasons: and it shall be, [that] every great matter they shall bring unto thee, but every small matter they shall judge: so shall it be easier for thyself, and they shall bear [the burden] with thee.

18:23

If thou shalt do this thing, and God command thee [so,] then

thou shalt be able to endure, and all this people shall also go to their place in peace.

18:24

So Moses hearkened to the voice of his father in law, and did all that he had said.

18:25

And Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people, rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens.

18:26

And they judged the people at all seasons: the hard causes they brought unto Moses, but every small matter they judged themselves.

18:27

And Moses let his father in law depart; and he went his way into his own land.

Exodus 19

Exodus

19:1

In the third month, when the children of Israel were gone forth out of the land of Egypt, the same day came they [into] the wilderness of Sinai.

19:2

For they were departed from Rephidim, and were come [to] the desert of Sinai, and had pitched in the wilderness; and there Israel camped before the mount.

19:3

And Moses went up unto

God, and the LORD called unto him out of the mountain

, saying, Thus shalt thou say to the house of Jacob, and tell the children ofIsrael;

19:4

Ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians, and [how] I bare you on eagles’ wings, and brought you unto myself.

19:5

Now therefore, if ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above all people: for all the earth [is] mine:

19:6

And ye shall be unto me a kingdom of priests, and an holy nation. These [are] the words which thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel.

19:7

And Moses came and called for the elders of the people, and laid before their faces all these words which the

LORD commanded him

.

19:8

And all the people answered together, and said, All that the LORD hath spoken we will do. And Moses returned the words of the people unto the LORD.

19:9

And the LORD said unto Moses, Lo, I come unto thee in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with thee, and believe thee for ever. And Moses told the words of the people unto the LORD.

19:10

And the LORD said unto Moses, Go unto the people, and sanctify them to day and to morrow, and let them wash their clothes,

19:11

And be ready against the third day: for the third day the LORD will come down in the sight of all the people upon mount Sinai.

19:12

And thou shalt set bounds unto the people round about, saying, Take heed to yourselves, [that ye] go [not] up into the mount, or touch the border of it: whosoever toucheth the mount shall be surely put to death:

19:13

There shall not an hand touch it, but he shall surely be stoned, or shot through; whether [it be] beast or man, it shall not live: when the trumpet soundeth long, they shall come up to the mount.

19:14

And Moses went down from the mount unto the people, and sanctified the people; and they washed their clothes.

19:15

And he said unto the people, Be ready against the third day: come not at [your] wives.

19:16

And it came to pass on the third day in the morning, that there were thunders and lightnings,

and a thick cloud upon the mount, and the voice of the trumpet exceeding loud; so that all the people that [was] in the camp trembled.

19:17

And Moses brought forth the people out of the camp to meet with God; and they stood at the nether part of the mount.

19:18

And mount Sinai was altogether on a smoke, because theLORD descended upon it in fire: and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace, and the whole mount quaked greatly.

19:19

And when the voice of the trumpet sounded long, and waxed louder and louder, Moses spake, and God answered him by a voice.

19:20

And the LORD came down upon mount Sinai, on the top of the mount: and the LORD called Moses [up] to the top of the mount; and Moses went up.

19:21

And the LORD said unto Moses, Go down, charge the people, lest they break through unto the LORD to gaze, and many of them perish.

19:22

And let the priests also, which come near to the LORD, sanctify themselves, lest the LORD break forth upon them.

19:23

And Moses said unto the LORD, The people cannot come up to mount Sinai: for thou chargedst us, saying, Set bounds about the mount, and sanctify it.

19:24

And the LORD said unto him, Away, get thee down, and thou shalt come up, thou, and Aaron with thee: but let not the priests and the people break through to come up unto the LORD, lest he break forth upon them.

19:25

So Moses went down unto the people, and spake unto them.

Exodus

33:1

And the LORD said unto Moses, Depart, [and] go up hence, thou and the people which thou hast brought up out of the land of Egypt, unto the land which I sware unto Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying,

Unto thy seed will I give it:

33:2

And I will send an angel before thee; and I will drive out the Canaanite, the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite:

33:3

Unto a land flowing with milk and honey: for I will not go up in the midst of thee; for thou [art] a stiffnecked people: lest I consume thee in the way.

33:4

And when the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned: and no man did put on him his ornaments.

33:5

For the LORD had said unto Moses, Say unto the children of Israel, Ye [are] a stiffnecked people: I will come up into the midst of thee in a moment, and consume thee: therefore now put off thy ornaments from thee, that I may know what to do unto thee.

33:6

And the children of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments by the mount Horeb.

33:7

And Moses took the tabernacle, and pitched it without the camp, afar off from the camp, andcalled it the Tabernacle of the congregation. And it came to pass, [that] every one which sought the LORD went out unto the tabernacle of the congregation, which [was] without the camp.

33:8

And it came to pass, when Moses went out unto the tabernacle, [that] all the people rose up, and stood every man [at] his tent door, and looked after Moses, until he was gone into the tabernacle.

33:9

And it came to pass, as Moses entered into the tabernacle, the cloudy pillar descended, and stood [at] the door of the tabernacle, and [the] LORD talked with Moses.

33:10

And all the people saw the cloudy pillar stand [at] the tabernacle door: and

all the people rose up and worshipped, every man [in] his tent door.

33:11

And the LORD spake unto Moses face to face, as a man speaketh unto his friend.

And he turned again into the camp: but his servant Joshua, the son of Nun, a young man, departed not out of the tabernacle.

33:12

And Moses said unto the LORD, See, thou sayest unto me, Bring up this people: and thou hast not let me know whom thou wilt send with me. Yet thou hast said, I know thee by name, and

thou hast also found grace in my sight.

33:13

Now therefore, I pray thee, if I have found grace in thy sight, shew me now thy way, that I may know thee, that I may find grace in thy sight: and consider that this nation [is] thy people.

33:14

And he said, My presence shall go [with thee,] and I will give thee rest.

33:15

And he said unto him, If thy presence go not [with me,] carry us not up hence.

33:16

For wherein shall it be known here that I and thy people have found grace in thy sight? [is it] not in that thou goest with us? so shall we be separated, I and thy people, from all the people that [are] upon the face of the earth.

33:17

And the LORD said unto Moses, I will do this thing also that thou hast spoken: for thou hast found grace in my sight, and I know thee by name.

33:18

And he said, I beseech thee, shew me thy glory.

33:19

And he said, I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and I will proclaim the name of the LORD before thee; and will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will shewmercy on whom I will shew mercy.

33:20

And he said, Thou canst not see my face: for there shall no man see me, and live.

33:21

And the LORD said, Behold, [there is] a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock:

33:22

And it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a clift of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by:

33:23

And I will take away mine hand, and thou shalt see my back parts: but my face shall not be seen.

Abraham

Genesis

12:1

Now the

LORD had said unto Abram, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and from thy father’s house, unto a land that I will shew thee:

12:2

And

I

will make of thee a great nation

, and

I

will bless thee, and make thy name great; and thou shalt be a blessing:

12:3

And

I

will bless them that bless thee, and curse him that curseth thee: and in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed

.

12:4

So Abram departed, as the LORD had spoken unto him; and Lot went with him: and Abram [was] seventy and five years old when he departed out of Haran.

12:5

And Abram took Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother’s son, and all their substance that they had gathered, and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came.

12:6

And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Sichem, unto the plain of Moreh. And the Canaanite [was] then in the land.

12:7

And the

LORD appeared unto Abram,

and said,

Unto thy seed will I give this land

: and

there builded he an altar unto the LORD

, who appeared unto him.

12:8

And he removed from thence unto a mountain on the east of Bethel, and pitched his tent, [having] Bethel on the west, and Hai on the east: and

there he builded an altar unto the LORD

, and called upon the name of the LORD.

12:9

And Abram journeyed, going on still toward the south.

12:10

And there was a famine in the land: and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there; for the famine [was] grievous in the land.

12:11

And it came to pass, when he was come near to enter into Egypt, that he said unto Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou [art] a fair woman to look upon:

12:12

Therefore it shallcome to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they shall say, This [is] his wife: and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive.

12:13

Say, I pray thee, thou [art] my sister: that it may be well with me for thy sake; and my soul shall live because of thee.

12:14

And it came to pass, that, when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she [was] very fair.

12:15

The princes also of Pharaoh saw her, and commended her before Pharaoh: and the woman was taken into Pharaoh’s house.

12:16

And he entreated Abram well for her sake: and he had sheep, and oxen, and he asses, and menservants, and maidservants, and she asses, and camels.

12:17

And the

LORD plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai Abram’s wife.

12:18

And Pharaoh called Abram, and said, What [is] this [that] thou hast done unto me? why didst thou not tell me that she [was] thy wife?

12:19

Why saidst thou, She [is] my sister? so I might have taken her to me to wife: now therefore behold thy wife, take [her,] and go thy way.

12:20

And Pharaoh commanded [his] men concerning him: and they sent him away, and his wife, and all that he had.

Genesis 17

Genesis

17:1

And when Abram was ninety years old and nine, the

LORD appeared to Abram, and said unto him, I [am] the Almighty God; walk before me, and be thou perfect.

17:2

And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly

.

17:3

And Abram fell on his face: and

God talked with him,

saying,

17:4

As for me, behold, my covenant [is] with thee, and

thou shalt be a father of many nations

.

17:5

Neither shall thy name any more be called Abram, but thy name shall be Abraham; for a father of many nations have I made thee.

17:6

And I will make thee exceeding fruitful, and I will make nations of thee, and kings shall come out of thee

.

17:7

And

I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee in their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy seed after thee.

17:8

And

I will give unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, the land wherein thou art a stranger, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting possession;

and

I will be their God.

17:9

And

God said unto Abraham, Thou shalt keep my covenant therefore, thou, and thy seed after thee in their generations.

17:10

This [is] my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me and you and thy seed after thee; Every man child among you shall be circumcised.

17:11

And ye shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be a token of the covenant betwixt me and you.

17:12

And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every man child in your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any stranger, which [is] not of thy seed.

17:13

He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised: and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant.

17:14

And the uncircumcised man child whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised,

that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my covenant

.

17:15

And

God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but Sarah [shall] her name [be.]

17:16

And

I will bless her,

and

give thee a son also of her: yea, I will bless her, and she shall be [a mother] of nations; kings of people shall be of her

.

17:17

Then Abraham fell upon his face, and laughed, and said in his heart, Shall [a child] be born unto him that is an hundred years old? and shall Sarah, that is ninety years old, bear?

17:18

And Abraham said unto God, O that Ishmael might live before thee!

17:19

And

God said,

Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed; and thou shalt call his name Isaac: and I will establish my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant, [and] with his seed after him

.

17:20

And as for Ishmael,

I have heard thee: Behold, I have

blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation

.

17:21

But my covenant will

I establish with Isaac, which Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year.

17:22

And he left off talking with him, and

God went up from Abraham.

17:23

And Abraham took Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham’s house; and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in the selfsame day, as God had said unto him.

17:24

And Abraham [was] ninety years old and nine, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin.

17:25

And Ishmael his son [was] thirteen years old, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin.

17:26

In the selfsame day was Abraham circumcised, and Ishmael his son.

17:27

And all the men of his house, born in the house, and bought with money of the stranger, were circumcised with him.

Genesis 22:1-14

Genesis

22:1

And it came to pass after these things, that

God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham: and he said, Behold, [here] I [am. ]

22:2

And he said, Take now thy son,

thine only [son] Isaac, whom thou lovest

, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and

offer him there for a burnt offering

upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.

22:3

And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and saddled his ass, and took two of his young men with him, and Isaac his son, and clave the wood for the burnt offering, and rose up, and went unto the place of which

God had told him

.

22:4

Then on the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes, and saw the place afar off.

22:5

And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide ye here with the ass; and I and the lad will go yonder and worship, and come again to you,

22:6

And Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering, and laid [it] upon Isaac his son; and he took the fire in his hand, and a knife; and they went both of them together.

22:7

And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here [am] I, my son. And he said, Behold the fire and the wood: but where [is] the lamb for a burnt offering?

22:8

And Abraham said, My son,

God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering

: so they went both of them together.

22:9

And they came to the place which

God had told him of

; and

Abraham built an altar there, and laid the wood in order, and bound Isaac his son, and laid him on the altar upon the wood.

22:10

And Abraham stretched forth his hand, and took the knife to slay his son.

22:11

And the angel of the LORD called unto him out of heaven, and said, Abraham, Abraham: and he said, Here [am] I.

22:12

And he said, Lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him: for now

I know that thou fearest God

, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only [son] from me.

22:13

And Abraham lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold behind [him] a ram caught in a thicket by his horns: and

Abraham went and took the ram, and offered him up for a burnt offering in the stead of his son.

22:14

And Abraham called the name of that place

Jehovah-jireh: as it is said [to] this day, In the mount of the LORD it shall be seen.

.

New Testament

Jesus

Luke

1:1

Forasmuch as many have taken in hand to

set forth in order a declaration of those things which are most surely believed among us

,

1:2

Even as they delivered them unto us, which from the beginning were eyewitnesses, and ministers of the word;

1:3

It seemed good to me also, having had perfect understanding of all things from the very first, to write unto thee in order, most excellent Theophilus,

1:4

That thou mightest know the certainty of those things

, wherein thou hast been instructed.

1:5

There was in the days of Herod, the king of Judaea, a certain priest named Zacharias, of the course of Abia: and his wife [was] of the daughters of Aaron, and her name [was] Elisabeth.

1:6

And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless

.

1:7

And they had no child, because that Elisabeth was barren, and they both were [now] well stricken in years.

1:8

And it came to pass, that

while he executed the priest’s office before God in the order of his course

,

1:9

According to the custom of the priest’s office, his lot was to burn incense when he went into the temple of the Lord.

1:10

And the whole

multitude of the people were praying without at the time of incense.

1:11

And there appeared unto him an angel of the Lord standing on the right side of the altar of incense.

1:12

And when Zacharias saw [him,] he was troubled, and fear fell upon him

.

1:13

But the angel

said unto him, Fear not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard; and thy wife Elisabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John

.

1:14

And thou shalt have joy and gladness; and many shall rejoice at his birth.

1:15

For he shall be great in the sight of the Lord

, and shall drink neither wine nor strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Ghost, even from his mother’s womb.

1:16

And many of the children of Israel shall he turn to the Lord their God.

1:17

And he shall go before him

in the spirit and power of Elias, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just; to make ready a people prepared for the Lord.

1:18

And Zacharias said unto the angel, Whereby shall I know this? for I am an old man, and my wife well stricken in years.

1:19

>And the angel answering said unto him, I am Gabriel, that stand in the presence of God

; and am sent to speak unto thee, and to shew thee these glad tidings.

1:20

And, behold, thou shalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that these things shall be performed, because thou believest not my words, which shall be fulfilled in their season.

1:21

And the people waited for Zacharias, and marvelled that he tarried so long in the temple.

1:22

And when he came out, he could not speak unto them: and they perceived that he had seen a vision in the temple: for he beckoned unto them, and remained speechless.

1:23

And it came to pass, that, as soon as the days of his ministration were accomplished, he departed to his own house.

1:24

And after those days his wife Elisabeth conceived, and hid herself five months, saying,

1:25

Thus hath the Lord dealt with me in the days wherein he looked on [me,] to take away my reproach among men

.

1:26

And in the sixth month

the angel Gabriel was sent from God unto a city of Galilee, named Nazareth

,

1:27

To a virgin espoused to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the virgin’s name [was] Mary.

1:28

And the angel came in unto her, and said,

Hail, [thou that art] highly favoured, the Lord [is] with thee: blessed [art] thou among women

.

1:29

And when she saw [him,] she was troubled at his saying, and cast in her mind what manner of salutation this should be.

1:30

And the angel said unto her,

Fear not, Mary

:

for thou hast found favour with God

.

1:31

And, behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a son, and shalt call his name JESUS.

1:32

He shall be great, and shall be called the Son of the Highest: and the Lord God shall give unto him the throne of his father David

:

1:33

And he shall reign over the house of Jacob for ever; and of his kingdom there shall be no end

.

1:34

Then said Mary unto the angel, How shall this be, seeing I know not a man?

1:35

And the angel answered and said unto her, The Holy Ghost shall come upon thee, and the power of the Highest shall overshadow thee: therefore also that holy thing which shall be born of thee shall be called the Son of God

.

1:36

And, behold, thy cousin Elisabeth, she hath also conceived a son in her old age: and this is the sixth month with her, who was called barren.

1:37

For with God nothing shall be impossible

.

1:38

And Mary said, Behold the handmaid of the Lord; be it unto me according to thy word. And the angel departed from her.

1:39

And Mary arose in those days, and went into the hill country with haste, into a city of Juda;

1:40

And entered into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elisabeth.

1:41

And it came to pass, that,

when Elisabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe leaped in her womb; and Elisabeth was filled with the Holy Ghost

:

1:42

And she spake out with a loud voice, and said,

Blessed [art] thou among women, and blessed [is] the fruit of thy womb

.

1:43

And whence [is] this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me?

1:44

For, lo, as soon as the voice of thy salutation sounded in mine ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy.

1:45

And blessed [is] she that believed: for there shall be a performance of those things which were told her from the Lord

.

1:46

And

Mary said, My soul doth magnify the Lord

,

1:47

And

my spirit hath rejoiced in God my Saviour

.

1:48

For he hath regarded the low estate of his handmaiden: for, behold, from henceforth all generations shall call me blessed

.

1:49

For he that is mighty hath done to me great things; and holy [is] his name

.

1:50

And his

mercy

[is] on them that

fear him from generation to generation

.

1:51

He hath shewed strength with his arm; he hath scattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts

.

1:52

He hath put down the mighty from [their] seats, and exalted them of low degree

.

1:53

He hath filled the hungry with good things; and the rich he hath sent empty away

.

1:54

He hath holpen his servant Israel, in remembrance of [his] mercy

;

1:55

As he spake to our fathers, to Abraham, and to his seed for ever.

1:56

And Mary abode with her about three months, and returned to her own house.

1:57

Now Elisabeth’s full time came that she should be delivered; and she brought forth a son.

1:58

And her neighbours and

her cousins heard how the Lord had shewed great mercy upon her; and they rejoiced with her

.

1:59

And it came to pass, that on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child; and they called him Zacharias, after the name of his father.

1:60

And his mother answered and said, Not [so;] but he shall be called John.

1:61

And they said unto her, There is none of thy kindred that is called by this name.

1:62

And they made signs to his father, how he would have him called.

1:63

And he asked for a writing table, and wrote, saying, His name is John. And they marvelled all.

1:64

And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue [loosed,] and he spake, and praised God

.

1:65

And fear came on all that dwelt round about them: and all these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill country of Judaea

.

1:66

And all they that heard [them] laid [them] up in their hearts, saying, What manner of child shall this be! And the hand of the Lord was with him.

1:67

And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Ghost, and prophesied, saying,

1:68

Blessed [be] the Lord God of Israel; for he hath visited and redeemed his people

,

1:69

And hath raised up an horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David;

1:70

As he spake by the mouth of his holy prophets, which have been since the world began:

1:71

That we should be saved from our enemies, and from the hand of all that hate us

;

1:72

To perform the mercy [promised] to our fathers, and to remember his holy covenant

;

1:73

The oath which he sware to our father Abraham,

1:74

That he would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hand of our enemies might serve him without fear

,

1:75

In holiness and righteousness before him, all the days of our life

.

1:76

And thou, child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest: for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to prepare his ways

;

1:77

To give knowledge of salvation unto his people by the remission of their sins

,

1:78

Through the tender mercy of our God; whereby the dayspring from on high hath visited us

,

1:79

To give light to them that sit in darkness and [in] the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace

.

1:80

And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, and was in the deserts till the day of his shewing unto Israel.

Luke

2:1

And it came to pass in those days, that there went out a decree from Caesar Augustus, that all the world should be taxed.

2:2

([And] this taxing was first made when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.)

2:3

And all went to be taxed, every one into his own city.

2:4

And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judaea, unto the city of David, which is called Bethlehem; (because he was of the house and lineage of David:)

2:5

To be taxed with Mary his espoused wife, being great with child.

2:6

And so it was, that, while they were there, the days were accomplished that she should be delivered.

2:7

And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn.

2:8

And there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.

2:9

And, lo,

the angel of the Lord came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about them: and they were sore afraid

.

2:10

And the angel said unto them,

Fear not

: for,

behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people

.

2:11

For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord.

2:12

And this [shall be] a sign unto you; Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, lying in a manger.

2:13

And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God

, and saying,

2:14

Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will toward men

.

2:15

And it came to pass, as

the angels were gone away from them into heaven

, the shepherds said one to another, Let us now go even unto Bethlehem, and see this thing which is come to pass, which the Lord hath made known unto us.

2:16

And they came with haste, and found Mary, and Joseph, and the babe lying in a manger.

2:17

And when they had seen [it,] they made known abroad the saying which was told them concerning this child.

2:18

And all they that heard [it] wondered at those things which were told them by the shepherds.

2:19

But Mary kept all these things, and pondered [them] in her heart.

2:20

And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, as it was told unto them

.

2:21

And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called JESUS, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.

2:22

And when the days of her purification according to the law of Moses were accomplished, they brought him to Jerusalem, to present [him] to the Lord

;

2:23

(As it is written in the law of the Lord, Every male that openeth the womb shall be called holy to the Lord;)

2:24

And

to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord, A pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons

.

2:25

And, behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name [was] Simeon; and the same man [was] just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel: and the Holy Ghost was upon him.

2:26

And it was revealed unto him by the Holy Ghost, that he should not see death, before he had seen the Lord’s Christ

.

2:27

And he came by the Spirit into the temple: and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him after the custom of the law,

2:28

Then took he him up in his arms, and blessed God

, and said,

2:29

Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, according to thy word

:

2:30

For mine eyes have seen thy salvation

,

2:31

Which thou hast prepared before the face of all people;

2:32

A light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people Israel.

2:33

And Joseph and his mother marvelled at those things which were spoken of him.

2:34

And Simeon blessed them, and said unto Mary his mother

,

Behold, this [child] is set for the fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against

;

2:35

(Yea, a sword shall pierce through thy own soul also,) that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed.

2:36

And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Aser: she was of a great age, and had lived with an husband seven years from her virginity;

2:37

And she [was] a widow of about fourscore and four years, which departed not from the temple, but

served [God] with fastings and prayers night and day

.

2:38

And she coming in that instant

gave thanks likewise unto the Lord

, and spake of him to all them that looked for redemption in Jerusalem.

2:39

And when they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned into Galilee, to their own city Nazareth.

2:40

And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him

.

2:41

Now his parents went to Jerusalem every year at the feast of the passover.

2:42

And when he was twelve years old, they went up to Jerusalem after the custom of the feast.

2:43

And when they had fulfilled the days, as they returned, the child Jesus tarried behind in Jerusalem; and Joseph and his mother knew not [of it. ]

2:44

But they, supposing him to have been in the company, went a day’s journey; and they sought him among [their] kinsfolk and acquaintance.

2:45

And when they found him not, they turned back again to Jerusalem, seeking him.

2:46

And it came to pass, that after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the doctors, both hearing them, and asking them questions.

2:47

And all that heard him were astonished at his understanding and answers.

2:48

And when they saw him, they were amazed: and his mother said unto him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing.

2:49

And he said unto them, How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father’s business?

2:50

And they understood not the saying which he spake unto them.

2:51

And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was subject unto them: but his mother kept all these sayings in her heart.

2:52

And

Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man

.

John

2:1

And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there:

2:2

And both Jesus was called, and his disciples, to the marriage.

2:3

And when they wanted wine, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine.

2:4

Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come.

2:5

His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do [it. ]

2:6

And there were set there six waterpots of stone, after the manner of the purifying of the Jews, containing two or three firkins apiece.

2:7

Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim.

2:8

And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the governor of the feast. And they bare [it. ]

2:9

When the ruler of the feast had tasted the water that was made wine, and knew not whence it was: (but the servants which drew the water knew;) the governor of the feast called the bridegroom,

2:10

And saith unto him, Every man at the beginning doth set forth good wine; and when men have well drunk, then that which is worse: [but] thou hast kept the good wine until now.

2:11

This beginning of miracles did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested forth his glory; and his disciples believed on him

.

Matthew

3:13

Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to Jordan unto John, to be baptized of him.

3:14

But John forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou to me?

3:15

And Jesus answering said unto him,

Suffer [it to be so] now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffered him

.

3:16

And

Jesus, when he was baptized, went up straightway out of the water: and, lo, the heavens were opened unto him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove, and lighting upon him

:

3:17

And lo a voice from

heaven

, saying,

This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased

.

Luke

8:22

Now it came to pass on a certain day, that he went into a ship with his disciples: and he said unto them, Let us go over unto the other side of the lake. And they launched forth.

8:23

But as they sailed he fell asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filled [with water,] and were in jeopardy.

8:24

And they came to him,

and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish

.

Then he arose, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm

.

8:25

And he said unto them, Where is your faith? And they being afraid wondered, saying one to another, What manner of man is this!

for

he commandeth even the winds and water, and they obey him

.

John

19:1

Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged [him. ]

19:2

And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put [it] on his head, and they put on him a purple robe,

19:3

And said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they smote him with their hands.

19:4

Pilate therefore went forth again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him.

19:5

Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And [Pilate] saith unto them, Behold the man!

19:6

When the chief priests therefore and officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify [him,] crucify [him.] Pilate saith unto them, Take ye him, and crucify [him:] for I find no fault in him.

19:7

The Jews answered him,

We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God

.

19:8

When

Pilate therefore heard that saying, he was the more afraid

;

19:9

And went again into the judgment hall, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer.

19:10

Then saith Pilate unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee, and have power to release thee?

19:11

Jesus answered,

Thou couldest have no power [at all] against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin

.

19:12

And from thenceforth Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Caesar’s friend: whosoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar.

19:13

When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus forth, and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew, Gabbatha.

19:14

And it was the preparation of the passover, and about the sixth hour: and he saith unto the Jews, Behold your King!

19:15

But they cried out, Away with [him,] away with [him,] crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.

19:16

Then delivered he him therefore unto them to be crucified. And they took Jesus, and led [him] away.

19:17

And he bearing his cross went forth into a place called [the place] of a skull, which is called in the Hebrew Golgotha:

19:18

Where they crucified him, and two others with him, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst.

19:19

And Pilate wrote a title, and put [it] on the cross. And the writing was, JESUS OF NAZARETH THE KING OF THE JEWS.

19:20

This title then read many of the Jews: for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city: and it was written in Hebrew, [and] Greek, [and] Latin.

19:21

Then said the chief priests of the Jews to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews.

19:22

Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.

19:23

Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments, and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also [his] coat: now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.

19:24

They said therefore among themselves, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith, They parted my raiment among them, and for my vesture they did cast lots. These things therefore the soldiers did.

19:25

Now there stood by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother’s sister, Mary the [wife] of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.

19:26

When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son!

19:27

Then saith he to the disciple, Behold thy mother! And from that hour that disciple took her unto his own [home. ]

19:28

After this, Jesus knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst.

19:29

Now there was set a vessel full of vinegar: and they filled a spunge with vinegar, and put [it] upon hyssop, and put [it] to his mouth.

19:30

When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said,

It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost

.

19:31

The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and [that] they might be taken away.

19:32

Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him.

19:33

But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs:

19:34

But one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and forthwith came there out blood and water.

19:35

And he that saw [it] bare record, and his record is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye might believe.

19:36

For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken

.

19:37

And again another scripture saith, They shall look on him whom they pierced.

19:38

And after this Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, besought Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave [him] leave. He came therefore, and took the body of Jesus

.

19:39

And there came also

Nicodemus, which at the first came to Jesus by night, and brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about an hundred pound [weight. ]

19:40

Then took they the body of Jesus, and wound it in linen clothes with the spices, as the manner of the Jews is to bury.

19:41

Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new sepulchre, wherein was never man yet laid.

19:42

There laid they Jesus therefore because of the Jews’ preparation [day;] for the sepulchre was nigh at hand.

Luke

23:26

And as they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon, a Cyrenian, coming out of the country, and on him they laid the cross, that he might bear [it] after Jesus.

23:27

And there followed him a great company of people, and of women, which also bewailed and lamented him.

23:28

But

Jesus turning unto them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children

.

23:29

For, behold, the days are coming, in the which they shall say,

Blessed [are] the barren, and the wombs that never bare, and the paps which never gave suck

.

23:30

Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us

.

23:31

For if they do these things in a green tree, what shall be done in the dry?

23:32

And there were also two others, malefactors, led with him to be put to death.

23:33

And when they were come to the place, which is called Calvary, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, and the other on the left.

23:34

Then said

Jesus, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots

.

23:35

And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also with them derided [him,] saying,

He saved others; let him save himself, if he be Christ, the chosen of God

.

23:36

And the soldiers also mocked him, coming to him, and offering him vinegar,

23:37

And saying, If thou be the king of the Jews, save thyself.

23:38

And a superscription also was written over him in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew, THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.

23:39

And one of the malefactors which were hanged railed on him, saying, If thou be Christ, save thyself and us.

23:40

But the other answering rebuked him, saying,

Dost not thou fear God

, seeing thou art in the same condemnation?

23:41

And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing amiss

.

23:42

And he said unto

Jesus, Lord, remember me when thou comest into thy kingdom

.

23:43

And Jesus said unto him,

Verily I say unto thee, To day shalt thou be with me in paradise

.

John

14:6

Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me

.

14:7

If ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also: and from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him

.

14:8

Philip saith unto him, Lord, shew us the Father, and it sufficeth us.

14:9

Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and yet hast thou not known me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; and how sayest thou [then,] Shew us the Father?

14:10

Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I speak unto you I speak not of myself: but the Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the works

.

14:11

Believe me that I [am] in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works’ sake

.

Philippians

2:5

Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:

2:6

Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God

:

2:7

But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men

:

2:8

And being found in fashion as a man,

he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross

.

Colossians

1:15

Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of every creature

:

1:16

For by him were all things created

,

that are in heaven

,

and that are in earth, visible and invisible, whether [they be] thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him

:

1:17

And he is before all things, and by him all things consist

.

1:18

And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all [things] he might have the preeminence

.

1:19

For it pleased [the Father] that in him should all fulness dwell

;

1:20

And,

having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself; by him, [I say,]

whether [they be] things in earth, or things in heaven

.

Luke

22:66

And as soon as it was day, the elders of the people and the chief priests and the scribes came together, and led him into their council, saying,

22:67

Art thou the Christ? tell us. And he said unto them, If I tell you, ye will not believe:

22:68

And if I also ask [you,] ye will not answer me, nor let [me] go.

22:69

Hereafter shall the Son of man sit on the right hand of the power of God

.

22:70

Then said they all, Art thou then the Son of God? And he said unto them, Ye say that I am

.

22:71

And they said,

What need we any further witness? for we ourselves have heard of his own mouth

.

Parables

Matthew

13:10

And the disciples came, and said unto him, Why speakest thou unto them in parables?

13:11

He answered and said unto them,

Because it is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of

heaven

,

but to them it is not given

.

13:12

For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that he hath

.

13:13

Therefore speak I to them in parables: because they seeing see not; and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand.

13:14

And in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Esaias, which saith, By hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive:

13:15

For this people’s heart is waxed gross, and [their] ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have closed; lest at any time they should see with [their] eyes, and hear with [their] ears, and should understand with [their] heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them

.

13:16

But blessed [are] your eyes, for they see: and your ears, for they hear

.

Revelations

Revelations

1:1

The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him, to shew unto his servants things which must shortly come to pass

; and he sent and signified [it] by his angel unto his servant John:

1:2

Who bare record of the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ

, and of all things that he saw.

1:3

Blessed [is] he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this prophecy, and keep those things which are written therein: for the time [is] at hand

.

1:4

John to the seven churches which are in Asia:

Grace [be] unto you, and peace, from him which is, and which was, and which is to come; and from the seven Spirits which are before his throne

;

1:5

And from Jesus Christ, [who is] the faithful witness, [and] the first begotten of the dead, and the prince of the kings of the earth. Unto him that loved us, and washed us from our sins in his own blood

,

1:6

And hath made us kings and priests unto God and his Father; to him [be] glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen

.

1:7

Behold, he cometh with clouds; and every eye shall see him, and they [also] which pierced him: and all kindreds of the earth shall wail because of him. Even so, Amen

.

1:8

I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the ending, saith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Almighty

.

1:9

I John, who also am your brother, and companion in tribulation, and in the kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ, was in the isle that is called Patmos, for the word of God, and for the testimony of Jesus Christ

.

1:10

I was in the Spirit on the Lord’s day, and heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet,

1:11

Saying, I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last: and,

What thou seest, write in a book, and send [it] unto the seven churches which are in Asia; unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamos, and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia, and unto Laodicea

.

1:12

And I turned to see the voice that spake with me. And being turned, I saw seven golden candlesticks;

1:13

And in the midst of the seven candlesticks [one] like unto the Son of man, clothed with a garment down to the foot, and girt about the paps with a golden girdle.

1:14

His head and [his] hairs [were] white like wool, as white as snow; and his eyes [were] as a flame of fire;

1:15

And his feet like unto fine brass, as if they burned in a furnace; and his voice as the sound of many waters.

1:16

And he had in his right hand seven stars: and out of his mouth went a sharp twoedged sword: and his countenance [was] as the sun shineth in his strength.

1:17

And when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead. And he laid his right hand upon me, saying unto me, Fear not; I am the first and the last

:

1:18

I [am] he that liveth, and was dead; and, behold, I am alive for evermore, Amen

; and

have the keys of hell and of death.

1:19

Write the things which thou hast seen, and the things which are, and the things which shall be hereafter;

1:20

The mystery of the seven stars which thou sawest in my right hand, and the seven golden candlesticks. The seven stars are the angels of the seven churches: and the seven candlesticks which thou sawest are the seven churches.

2:1

Unto the angel of the church of Ephesus write; These things saith he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, who walketh in the midst of the seven golden candlesticks;

2:2

I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canst not bear them which are evil: and thou hast tried them which say they are apostles, and are not, and hast found them liars:

2:3

And hast borne, and hast patience, and for my name’s sake hast laboured, and hast not fainted.

2:4

Nevertheless I have [somewhat] against thee, because thou hast left thy first love

.

2:5

Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the first works; or else I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy candlestick out of his place, except thou repent.

2:6

But this thou hast, that thou hatest the deeds of the Nicolaitanes, which I also hate.

2:7

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life, which is in the midst of the paradise of God

.

2:8

And unto the angel of the church in Smyrna write; These things saith the first and the last, which was dead, and is alive;

2:9

I know thy works, and tribulation, and poverty, (but thou art rich) and [I know] the blasphemy of them which say they are Jews, and are not, but [are] the synagogue of Satan.

2:10

Fear none of those things which thou shalt suffer

: behold, the devil shall cast [some] of you into prison, that ye may be tried; and ye shall have tribulation ten days: be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life.

2:11

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; He that overcometh shall not be hurt of the second death.

2:12

And to the angel of the church in Pergamos write; These things saith he which hath the sharp sword with two edges;

2:13

I know thy works, and where thou dwellest, [even] where Satan’s seat [is:] and thou holdest fast my name, and hast not denied my faith, even in those days wherein Antipas [was] my faithful martyr, who was slain among you, where Satan dwelleth.

2:14

But I have a few things against thee, because thou hast there them that hold the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balac to cast a stumblingblock before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed unto idols, and to commit fornication.

2:15

So hast thou also them that hold the doctrine of the Nicolaitanes, which thing I hate.

2:16

Repent; or else I will come unto thee quickly, and will fight against them with the sword of my mouth.

2:17

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches; To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the hidden manna, and will give him a white stone, and in the stone a new name written, which no man knoweth saving he that receiveth [it. ]

2:18

And unto the angel of the church in Thyatira write;

These things saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like unto a flame of fire, and his feet [are] like fine brass

;

2:19

I know thy works, and charity, and service, and faith, and thy patience, and thy works; and the last [to be] more than the first.

2:20

Notwithstanding I have a few things against thee, because thou sufferest that woman Jezebel, which calleth herself a prophetess, to teach and to seduce my servants to commit fornication, and to eat things sacrificed unto idols.

2:21

And I gave her space to repent of her fornication; and she repented not.

2:22

Behold, I will cast her into a bed, and them that commit adultery with her into great tribulation, except they repent of their deeds.

2:23

And I will kill her children with death; and all the churches shall know that I am he which searcheth the reins and hearts: and I will give unto every one of you according to your works.

2:24

But unto you I say, and unto the rest in Thyatira, as many as have not this doctrine, and which have not known the depths of Satan, as they speak; I will put upon you none other burden.

2:25

But that which ye have [already] hold fast till I come.

2:26

And he that overcometh, and keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give power over the nations:

2:27

And he shall rule them with a rod of iron; as the vessels of a potter shall they be broken to shivers: even as I received of my Father.

2:28

And I will give him the morning star.

2:29

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

3:1

And unto the angel of the church in Sardis write;

These things saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars; I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and art dead

.

3:2

Be watchful, and strengthen the things which remain, that are ready to die: for I have not found thy works perfect before God

.

3:3

Remember therefore how thou hast received and heard, and hold fast, and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come on thee as a thief, and thou shalt not know what hour I will come upon thee.

3:4

Thou hast a few names even in Sardis which have not defiled their garments; and they shall walk with me in white: for they are worthy.

3:5

He that overcometh, the same shall be clothed in white raiment; and I will not blot out his name out of the book of life, but I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels.

3:6

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

3:7

And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write; These things saith he that is holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of David, he that openeth, and no man shutteth; and shutteth, and no man openeth;

3:8

I know thy works: behold, I have set before thee an open door, and no man can shut it: for thou hast a little strength, and hast kept my word, and hast not denied my name.

3:9

Behold, I will make them of the synagogue of Satan, which say they are Jews, and are not, but do lie; behold, I will make them to come and worship before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee.

3:10

Because thou hast kept the word of my patience, I also will keep thee from the hour of temptation, which shall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth.

3:11

Behold, I come quickly: hold that fast which thou hast, that no man take thy crown.

3:12

Him that overcometh will I make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go no more out: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, [which is] new Jerusalem, which cometh down out of

heaven

from my God: and [I will write upon him] my new name

.

3:13

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

3:14

And unto the angel of the church of the Laodiceans write;

These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God

;

3:15

I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wert cold or hot.

3:16

So then because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth.

3:17

Because thou sayest, I am rich, and increased with goods, and have need of nothing; and knowest not that thou art wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked:

3:18

I counsel thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou mayest be rich; and white raiment, that thou mayest be clothed, and [that] the shame of thy nakedness do not appear; and anoint thine eyes with eyesalve, that thou mayest see.

3:19

As many as I

love

, I rebuke and chasten: be zealous therefore, and repent.

3:20

Behold, I stand at the door, and knock: if any man hear my voice, and open the door, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he with me.

3:21

To him that overcometh will I grant to sit with me in my throne, even as I also overcame, and am set down with my Father in his throne

.

3:22

He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith unto the churches.

Revelations

8:1

And when he had opened the seventh seal, there was silence in

heaven

about the space of half an hour.

8:2

And I saw the seven angels which stood before God

; and to them were given seven trumpets.

8:3

And another angel came and stood at the altar, having a golden censer; and there was given unto him much incense, that he should offer [it] with the prayers of all saints upon the golden altar which was before the throne.

8:4

And the smoke of the incense, [which came] with the prayers of the saints, ascended up before God

out of the angel’s hand.

8:5

And the angel took the censer, and filled it with fire of the altar, and cast [it] into the earth: and there were voices, and thunderings, and lightnings, and an earthquake.

8:6

And the seven angels which had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound.

8:7

The first angel sounded, and there followed hail and fire mingled with blood, and they were cast upon the earth: and the third part of trees was burnt up, and all green grass was burnt up.

8:8

And the second angel sounded, and as it were a great mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea: and the third part of the sea became blood;

8:9

And the third part of the creatures which were in the sea, and had life, died; and the third part of the ships were destroyed.

8:10

And the third angel sounded, and there fell a great star from

heaven

, burning as it were a lamp, and it fell upon the third part of the rivers, and upon the fountains of waters;

8:11

And the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter

.

8:12

And the fourth angel sounded, and the third part of the sun was smitten, and the third part of the moon, and the third part of the stars; so as the third part of them was darkened, and the day shone not for a third part of it, and the night likewise.

8:13

And I beheld, and heard an angel flying through the midst of

heaven

, saying with a loud voice,

Woe, woe, woe, to the inhabiters of the earth by reason of the other voices of the trumpet of the three angels, which are yet to sound

!

9:1

And the fifth angel sounded, and I saw a star fall from

heaven

unto the earth: and to him was given the key of the bottomless pit.

9:2

And he opened the bottomless pit; and there arose a smoke out of the pit, as the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the air were darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit.

9:3

And there came out of the smoke locusts upon the earth: and unto them was given power, as the scorpions of the earth have power.

9:4

And it was commanded them that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree; but only those men which have not the seal of God in their foreheads

.

9:5

And to them it was given that they should not kill them, but that they should be tormented five months: and their torment [was] as the torment of a scorpion, when he striketh a man

.

9:6

And in those days shall men seek death, and shall not find it; and shall desire to die, and death shall flee from them

.

9:7

And the shapes of the locusts [were] like unto horses prepared unto battle; and on their heads [were] as it were crowns like gold, and their faces [were] as the faces of men.

9:8

And they had hair as the hair of women, and their teeth were as [the teeth] of lions.

9:9

And they had breastplates, as it were breastplates of iron; and the sound of their wings [was] as the sound of chariots of many horses running to battle.

9:10

And they had tails like unto scorpions, and there were stings in their tails: and their power [was] to hurt men five months.

9:11

And they had a king over them, [which is] the angel of the bottomless pit, whose name in the Hebrew tongue [is] Abaddon, but in the Greek tongue hath [his] name Apollyon.

9:12

One woe is past; [and,] behold, there come two woes more hereafter

.

9:13

And the sixth angel sounded, and

I heard a voice from the four horns of the golden altar which is before God

,

9:14

Saying to the sixth angel which had the trumpet, Loose the four angels which are bound in the great river Euphrates.

9:15

And the four angels were loosed, which were prepared for an hour, and a day, and a month, and a year, for to slay the third part of men

.

9:16

And the number of the army of the horsemen [were] two hundred thousand thousand: and I heard the number of them.

9:17

And thus I saw the horses in the vision, and them that sat on them, having breastplates of fire, and of jacinth, and brimstone: and the heads of the horses [were] as the heads of lions; and out of their mouths issued fire and smoke and brimstone.

9:18

By these three was the third part of men killed, by the fire, and by the smoke, and by the brimstone, which issued out of their mouths

.

9:19

For their power is in their mouth, and in their tails: for their tails [were] like unto serpents, and had heads, and with them they do hurt.

9:20

And the rest of the men which were not killed by these plagues yet repented not of the works of their hands, that they should not worship devils, and idols of gold, and silver, and brass, and stone, and of wood: which neither can see, nor hear, nor walk

:

9:21

Neither repented they of their murders, nor of their sorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of their thefts.

10:1

And I saw another mighty angel come down from

heaven

, clothed with a cloud: and a rainbow [was] upon his head, and his face [was] as it were the sun, and his feet as pillars of fire:

10:2

And he had in his hand a little book open: and he set his right foot upon the sea, and [his] left [foot] on the earth,

10:3

And cried with a loud voice, as [when] a lion roareth: and when he had cried, seven thunders uttered their voices.

10:4

And when the seven thunders had uttered their voices, I was about to write: and I heard a voice from

heaven

saying unto me, Seal up those things which the seven thunders uttered, and write them not.

10:5

And the angel which I saw stand upon the sea and upon the earth lifted up his hand to

heaven

,

10:6

And sware by him that liveth for ever and ever, who created

heaven

,

and the things that therein are, and the earth, and the things that therein are, and the sea, and the things which are therein, that there should be time no longer

:

10:7

But in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he shall begin to sound,

the mystery of God should be finished, as he hath declared to his servants the prophets

.

10:8

And the voice which I heard from

heaven

spake unto me again, and said, Go [and] take the little book which is open in the hand of the angel which standeth upon the sea and upon the earth.

10:9

And I went unto the angel, and said unto him, Give me the little book. And he said unto me, Take [it,] and eat it up; and it shall make thy belly bitter, but it shall be in thy mouth sweet as honey.

10:10

And I took the little book out of the angel’s hand, and ate it up; and it was in my mouth sweet as honey: and as soon as I had eaten it, my belly was bitter.

10:11

And he said unto me, Thou must prophesy again before many peoples, and nations, and tongues, and kings.

11:1

And there was given me a reed like unto a rod: and the angel stood, saying,

Rise, and measure the temple of God

, and the altar, and them that worship therein.

11:2

But the court which is without the temple leave out, and measure it not; for it is given unto the Gentiles: and the holy city shall they tread under foot forty [and] two months.

11:3

And I will give [power] unto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred [and] threescore days, clothed in sackcloth

.

11:4

These are the

two olive trees, and the two candlesticks standing before the God of the earth

.

11:5

And if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, he must in this manner be killed

.

11:6

These have power to shut

heaven

, that it rain not in the days of their prophecy: and have power over waters to turn them to blood, and to smite the earth with all plagues, as often as they will.

11:7

And when they shall have finished their testimony, the beast that ascendeth out of the bottomless pit shall make war against them, and shall overcome them, and kill them

.

11:8

And their dead bodies [shall lie] in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also our Lord was crucified

.

11:9

And they of the people and kindreds and tongues and nations shall see their dead bodies three days and an half, and shall not suffer their dead bodies to be put in graves.

11:10

And they that dwell upon the earth shall rejoice over them, and make merry, and shall send gifts one to another; because these two prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.

11:11

And after three days and an half the Spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feet

; and

great fear fell upon them which saw them

.

11:12

And they heard a great voice from

heaven

saying unto them, Come up hither. And they ascended up to

heaven

in a cloud; and their enemies beheld them.

11:13

And the same hour was there a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city fell, and in the earthquake were slain of men seven thousand: and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of

heaven

.

11:14

The second woe is past; [and,] behold, the third woe cometh quickly.

11:15

And the seventh angel sounded; and there were great voices in

heaven

, saying,

The kingdoms of this world are become [the kingdoms] of our Lord, and of his Christ; and he shall reign for ever and ever

.

11:16

And the four and twenty elders,

which sat before God on their seats, fell upon their faces, and worshipped God

,

11:17

Saying,

We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art, and wast, and art to come; because thou hast taken to thee thy great power, and hast reigned

.

11:18

And the nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead, that they should be judged, and that thou shouldest give reward unto thy servants the prophets, and to the saints, and

them that fear thy name

, small and great; and shouldest destroy them which destroy the earth.

11:19

And the temple of God was opened in

heaven

,

and there was seen in his temple the ark of his testament: and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunderings, and an earthquake, and great hail

.

Revelations

21:1

And I saw a new

heaven

and a new earth: for the first

heaven

and the first earth were passed away; and there was no more sea.

21:2

And I John saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of

heaven

, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.

21:3

And I heard a great voice out of

heaven

saying,

Behold, the tabernacle of God [is] with men, and he will dwell with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself shall be with them, [and be] their God

.

21:4

And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there shall be no more death, neither sorrow, nor crying, neither shall there be any more pain: for the former things are passed away

.

21:5

And he that sat upon the throne said,

Behold, I make all things new. And he said unto me, Write: for these words are true and faithful

.

21:6

And he said unto me, It is done.

I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely

.

21:7

He that overcometh shall inherit all things; and I will be his God, and he shall be my son

.

21:8

But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death

.

21:9

And there came unto me one of the seven angels which had the seven vials full of the seven last plagues, and talked with me, saying, Come hither, I will shew thee the bride, the Lamb’s wife.

21:10

And he carried me away in the spirit to a great and high mountain, and

shewed me that great city, the holy Jerusalem, descending out of

heaven

from God

,

21:11

Having the glory of God: and her light [was] like unto a stone most precious, even like a jasper stone, clear as crystal

;

21:12

And had a wall great and high, [and] had twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, and names written thereon, which are [the names] of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel

:

21:13

On the east three gates; on the north three gates; on the south three gates; and on the west three gates.

21:14

And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and in them the names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb

.

21:15

And he that talked with me had a golden reed to measure the city, and the gates thereof, and the wall thereof.

21:16

And the city lieth foursquare, and the length is as large as the breadth: and he measured the city with the reed, twelve thousand furlongs. The length and the breadth and the height of it are equal.

21:17

And he measured the wall thereof, an hundred [and] forty [and] four cubits, [according to] the measure of a man, that is, of the angel.

21:18

And the building of the wall of it was [of] jasper: and the city [was] pure gold, like unto clear glass.

21:19

And the foundations of the wall of the city [were] garnished with all manner of precious stones. The first foundation [was] jasper; the second, sapphire; the third, a chalcedony; the fourth, an emerald;

21:20

The fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardius; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, a topaz; the tenth, a chrysoprasus; the eleventh, a jacinth; the twelfth, an amethyst.

21:21

And the twelve gates [were] twelve pearls; every several gate was of one pearl: and the street of the city [was] pure gold, as it were transparent glass.

21:22

And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple of it

.

21:23

And the city had no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb [is] the light thereof

.

21:24

And the nations of them which are saved shall walk in the light of it: and the kings of the earth do bring their glory and honour into it

.

21:25

And the gates of it shall not be shut at all by day: for there shall be no night there.

21:26

And they shall bring the glory and honour of the nations into it

.

21:27

And there shall in no wise enter into it any thing that defileth, neither [whatsoever] worketh abomination, or [maketh] a lie: but they which are written in the Lamb’s book of life.

22:1

And he shewed me a pure river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb

.

22:2

In the midst of the street of it, and on either side of the river, [was there] the tree of life, which bare twelve [manner] of fruits, [and] yielded her fruit every month: and the leaves of the tree [were] for the healing of the nations.

22:3

And there shall be no more curse:

but the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it; and his servants shall serve him

:

22:4

And they shall see his face; and his name [shall be] in their foreheads.

22:5

And there shall be no night there; and they need no candle, neither light of the sun;

for the Lord God giveth them light

: and they shall reign for ever and ever.

22:6

And he said unto me,

These sayings [are] faithful and true: and the Lord God of the holy prophets sent his angel to shew unto his servants the things which must shortly be done

.

22:7

Behold, I come quickly: blessed is he that keepeth the sayings of the prophecy of this book

.

22:8

And I John saw these things, and heard [them.] And when I had heard and seen,

I fell down to worship before the feet of the angel which shewed me these things

.

22:9

Then saith he unto me,

See [thou do it] not: for I am thy fellowservant, and of thy brethren the prophets, and of them which keep the sayings of this book: worship God

.

22:10

And he saith unto me, Seal not the sayings of the prophecy of this book: for the time is at hand.

22:11

He that is unjust, let him be unjust still: and he which is filthy, let him be filthy still: and he that is righteous, let him be righteous still: and he that is holy, let him be holy still

.

22:12

And, behold, I come quickly; and my reward [is] with me, to give every man according as his work shall be.

22:13

I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and the last

.

22:14

Blessed [are] they that do his commandments, that they may have right to the tree of life

, and

may enter in through the gates into the city

.

22:15

For without [are] dogs, and sorcerers, and whoremongers, and murderers, and idolaters, and whosoever loveth and maketh a lie

.

22:16

I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify unto you these things in the churches. I am the root and the offspring of David, [and] the bright and morning star

.

22:17

And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come. And let him that is athirst come. And whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely

.

22:18

For I testify unto every man that heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, If any man shall add unto these things, God shall add unto him the plagues that are written in this book

:

22:19

And if any man shall take away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part out of the book of life, and out of the holy city, and [from] the things which are written in this book

.

22:20

He which testifieth these things saith, Surely I come quickly. Amen. Even so, come, Lord Jesus.

Abraham

Hebrews

11:8

By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which he should after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out, not knowing whither he went

.

11:9

By faith he sojourned in the land of promise, as [in] a strange country, dwelling in tabernacles with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise

:

11:10

For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker [is] God

.

James

2:21

Was not Abraham our father justified by works, when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar

.

Quran

Creation

chapter 14

32

God

is He Who created the

heavens

s and the earth, and sends down water from the sky, and with it produces fruits for your sustenance. And He committed the ships to your service, sailing through the sea by His command, and He committed the rivers to your service.

33

And He committed the sun and the moon to your service, both continuously pursuing their courses, and He committed the night and the day to your service.

34

And He has given you something of all what you asked. And if you were to count

God

’s

blessings

, you would not be able to enumerate them. The human being is unfair and ungrateful.

chapter 23

12

We created man from an extract of clay.

13

Then We made him a seed, in a secure repository.

14

Then We developed the seed into a clot. Then We developed the clot into a lump. Then We developed the lump into bones. Then We clothed the bones with flesh. Then We produced it into another creature. Most Blessed is

God

, the Best of Creators.

chapter 35

1

Praise be to

God

, Originator of the

heavens

s and the earth, Maker of the angels messengers with wings—double, triple, and quadruple. He adds to creation as He wills.

God

is Able to do all things.

chapter 39

62

God

is the Creator of all things, and He is in Charge of all things.

chapter 40

57

Certainly the creation of the

heavens

s and the earth is greater than the creation of humanity, but most people do not know.

67

verse is He who created you from dust, then from a seed, then from an embryo, then He brings you out as an infant, then He lets you reach your maturity, then you become elderly—although some of you die sooner—so that you may reach a predetermined age, so that you may understand.

68

verse is He who gives life and death; and when He decides on a thing, He just says to it, “Be,” and it comes to be.

chapter 50

38

We created the

heavens

s and the earth and what is between them in six days, and no fatigue touched Us.

chapter 65

12

God

is He Who created seven

heavens

s, and their like of earth. The command descends through them, so that you may know that

God

is Capable of everything, and that

God

Encompasses everything in knowledge.

Revelations

chapter 14

48

On the Day when the earth is changed into another earth, and the

heavens

s, and they will emerge before

God

, the One, the verseresistible.

49

On that Day, you will see the sinners bound together in chains.

50

Their garments made of tar, and the Fire covering their faces.

51

That

God

may repay each soul according to what it has earned.

God

is Quick in reckoning.

52

This is a proclamation for mankind, that they may be warned thereby, and know that He is One

God

, and that people of understanding may remember.

chapter 50

41

And listen for the Day when the caller calls from a nearby place.

42

The Day when they will hear the Shout in all truth. That is the Day of Emergence.

43

verse is We who control life and death, and to Us is the destination.

44

The Day when the earth will crack for them at once. That is an easy gathering for Us.

45

We are fully aware of what they say, and you are not a dictator over them. So remind by the Quran whoever fears My warning.

chapter 69

13

Then, when the Trumpet is sounded a single time.

14

And the earth and the mountains are lifted up, and crushed, with a single crush.

15

On that Day, the Event will come to pass.

16

And the

heavens

will crack; so on that Day it will be frail.

17

And the angels will be ranged around its borders, while eight will be carrying the Throne of your verserd above them that Day.

18

On that Day you will be exposed, and no secret of yours will remain hidden.

19

As for him who is given his book in his right hand, he will say, “Here, take my book and read it.

20

he knew he would be held accountable.”

21

So he will be in pleasant living.

22

verse a lofty Garden.

23

verses pickings are within reach.

24

“Eat and drink merrily for what you did in the days gone by.”

25

But as for him who is given his book in his left hand, he will say, “versewish versewas never given my book.

26

And never knew what my account was.

27

verse only it was the end.

28

My money cannot avail me.

29

My power has vanished from me.”

30

“Take him and shackle him.

31

Then scorch him in the Blaze.

32

Then in a chain which length is seventy cubits tie him up.

33

For he would not believe in

God

the Great.

34

Nor would he advocate the feeding of the destitute.

35

So he has no friend here today.

36

And no food except scum.

37

Which only the sinners eat.”

chapter 73

14

On the Day when the earth and the mountains tremble, and the mountains become heaps of sand.

Parables

chapter 4

36

worship

God

, and ascribe no partners to Him, and be good to the parents, and the relatives, and the orphans, and the poor, and the neighbor next door, and the distant neighbor, and the close associate, and the traveler, and your servants.

God

does not

love

the arrogant showoff.

37

Those who are stingy, and exhort people to stinginess, and conceal what

God

has given them from His bounty. We have prepared for the disbelievers a disgraceful punishment.

chapter 14

25

verse yields its fruits every season by the will of its verserd.

God

presents the parables to the people, so that they may reflect.

26

And the parable of a bad word is that of a bad tree—it is uprooted from the ground; it has no stability.

27

God

gives firmness to those who believe, with the firm word, in this life, and in the Hereafter. And

God

leads the wicked astray.

God

does whatever He wills.

Noah and the Flood

chapter 11

25

We sent Noah to his people, “verseam to you a clear warner.”

26

“That you shall

worship

none but

God

. versefear for you the agony of a painful Day.”

27

The notables who disbelieved among his people said, “We see in you nothing but a man like us, and we see that only the worst among us have followed you, those of immature judgment. And we see that you have no advantage over us. verse fact, we think you are liars.”

28

He said, “O my people, Have you considered? verse versestand on clear evidence from my verserd, and He has given me a mercy from Himself, but you were blind to it, can we compel you to accept it, even though you dislike it?”

29

“O my people! verseask of you no money for it. My reward lies only with

God

. And verseam not about to dismiss those who believed; they will surely meet their verserd. And versesee that you are ignorant people.”

30

“O my people! Who will support me against

God

, if versedismiss them? Will you not give a thought?”

31

“versedo not say to you that versepossess the treasures of

God

, nor do verseknow the future, nor do versesay that verseam an angel. Nor do versesay of those who are despicable in your eyes that

God

will never give them any good.

God

is Aware of what lies in their souls. verse versedid, versewould be one of the wrongdoers.”

32

They said, “O Noah, you have argued with us, and argued a great deal. Now bring upon us what you threaten us with, if you are truthful.”

33

He said, “verse is

God

who will bring it upon you, if He wills, and you will not be able to escape.”

34

“My advice will not benefit you, much as versemay want to advise you, if

God

desires to confound you. He is your verserd, and to Him you will be returned.”

35

Or do they say, “He made it up?” Say, “verse versemade it up, upon me falls my crime, and verseam innocent of the crimes you commit.”

36

And it was revealed to Noah: “None of your people will believe, except those who have already believed, so do not grieve over what they do.”

37

“And build the Ark, under Our eyes, and with Our inspiration, and do not address Me regarding those who did wrong; they are to be drowned.”

38

As he was building the ark, whenever some of his people passed by him, they ridiculed him. He said, “verse you ridicule us, we will ridicule you, just as you ridicule.”

39

“You will surely know upon whom will come a torment that will abase him, and upon whom will fall a lasting torment.”

40

Until, when Our command came, and the volcano erupted, We said, “Board into it a pair of every kind, and your family—except those against whom the sentence has already been passed—and those who have believed.” But those who believed with him were only a few.

41

He said, “Embark in it. verse the name of

God

shall be its sailing and its anchorage. My verserd is indeed Forgiving and Merciful.”

42

And so it sailed with them amidst waves like hills. And Noah called to his son, who had kept away, “O my son! Embark with us, and do not be with the disbelievers.”

43

He said, “versewill take refuge on a mountain—it will protect me from the water.” He said, “There is no protection from

God

’s decree today, except for him on whom He has mercy.” And the waves surged between them, and he was among the drowned.

44

And it was said, “O earth, swallow your waters,” and “O

heavens

, clear up.” And the waters receded, and the event was concluded, and it settled on Judi, and it was proclaimed: “Away with the wicked people.”

45

And Noah called to his verserd. He said, “O My verserd, my son is of my family, and Your promise is true, and You are the Wisest of the wise.”

46

He said, “O Noah, he is not of your family. verse is an unrighteous deed. So do not ask Me about something you know nothing about. verseadmonish you, lest you be one of the ignorant.”

47

He said, “O My verserd, verseseek refuge with You, from asking You about what versehave no knowledge of. Unless You forgive me, and have mercy on me, versewill be one of the losers.”

48

verse was said, “O Noah, disembark with peace from Us; and with

blessings

upon you, and upon communities from those with you. And other communities We will grant prosperity, and then a painful torment from Us will befall them.”

chapter 23

23

We sent Noah to his people. He said, “O my people,

worship

God

, you have no deity other than Him. Will you not take heed?”

24

But the notables of his people, who disbelieved, said, “This is nothing but a human like you, who wants to gain superiority over you. Had

God

willed, He would have sent down angels. We never heard of this from our forefathers of old.

25

He is nothing but a man possessed. Just ignore him for a while.”

26

He said, “My verserd, help me, for they have rejected me.”

27

So We inspired him: “Build the Ark under Our observation and by Our inspiration. And when Our decree comes to pass, and the oven boils over, load into it two pairs of every kind, together with your family, except those of them against whom the word has already been pronounced. And do not speak to me concerning those who did wrong; for they are to be drowned.”

28

Then, when you and those with you are settled in the Ark, say, “Praise be to

God

, who has saved us from the wrongdoing people.”

29

And say, “My verserd, land me with a blessed landing, as you are the best of transporters.”

30

Surely in that are signs. We are always testing.

chapter 71

1

We sent Noah to his people: “Warn your people before there comes upon them a painful punishment.”

2

He said, “O my people, verseam to you a clear warner.

3

worship

God

and reverence Him, and obey me.

4

And He will forgive you of your sins, and reprieve you until a stated term.

God

’s term cannot be deferred once it has arrived, if you only knew.”

5

He said, “My verserd, versehave called my people night and day.

6

But my call added only to their flight.

7

Whenever versecalled them to Your forgiveness, they thrust their fingers into their ears, and wrapped themselves in their garments, and insisted, and became more and more arrogant.

8

Then versecalled them openly.

9

Then verseappealed to them publicly, and versespoke to them privately.

10

versesaid, ‘Ask your verserd for forgiveness; He is Forgiving.

11

He will let loose the sky upon you in torrents.

12

And provide you with wealth and children, and allot for you gardens, and allot for you rivers.

13

What is the matter with you, that you do not appreciate

God

’s Greatness?

14

Although He created you in stages.

15

Do you not realize that

God

created seven

heavens

s in layers?

16

And He set the moon in their midst for light, and He made the sun a lamp.

17

And

God

germinated you from the earth like plants.

18

Then He will return you into it, and will bring you out again.

19

And

God

made the earth a spread for you.

20

That you may travel its diverse roads.’”

21

Noah said, “My verserd, they have defied me, and followed him whose wealth and children increase him only in perdition.”

22

And they schemed outrageous schemes.

23

And they said, “Do not give up your

God

s; do not give up Wadd, nor Souwa, nor Yaghoos, and Yaooq, and Nassr.

24

They have misled many, so do not increase the wrongdoers except in confusion.”

25

Because of their wrongs, they were drowned, and were hurled into a Fire. They did not find apart from

God

any helpers.

26

Noah said, “My verserd, do not leave of the unbelievers a single dweller on earth.

27

verse You leave them, they will mislead your servants, and will breed only wicked unbelievers.

28

My verserd! Forgive me and my parents, and anyone who enters my home in faith, and all the believing men and believing women; and do not increase the wrongdoers except in perdition.”

Moses

chapter 4

164

Do not give the immature your money which

God

has assigned to you for support. But provide for them from it, and clothe them, and speak to them with kind words.

165

Test the orphans until they reach the age of marriage. verse you find them to be mature enough, hand over their properties to them. And do not consume it extravagantly or hastily before they grow up. The rich shall not charge any wage, but the poor may charge fairly. When you hand over their properties to them, have it witnessed for them.

God

suffices as a Reckoner.

166

Men receive a share of what their parents and relatives leave, and women receive a share of what their parents and relatives leave; be it little or much—a legal share.

167

verse the distribution is attended by the relatives, and the orphans, and the needy, give them something out of it, and speak to them kindly.

168

Those who are concerned about the fate of their weak children, in case they leave them behind, should fear

God

, and speak appropriate words.

169

Those who consume the wealth of orphans illicitly consume only fire into their bellies; and they will roast in a Blaze.

170

God

instructs you regarding your children: The male receives the equivalent of the share of two females. verse they are daughters, more than two, they get two-thirds of what he leaves. verse there is only one, she gets one-half. As for the parents, each gets one-sixth of what he leaves, if he had children. verse he had no children, and his parents inherit from him, his mother gets one-third. verse he has siblings, his mother gets one-sixth. After fulfilling any bequest and paying off debts. Your parents and your children—you do not know which are closer to you in welfare. This is

God

's versew.

God

is Knowing and Judicious.

171

You get one-half of what your wives leave behind, if they had no children. verse they had children, you get one-fourth of what they leave. After fulfilling any bequest and paying off debts. They get one-fourth of what you leave behind, if you have no children. verse you have children, they get one-eighth of what you leave. After fulfilling any bequest and paying off debts. verse a man or woman leaves neither parents nor children, but has a brother or sister, each of them gets one-sixth. verse there are more siblings, they share one-third. After fulfilling any bequest and paying off debts, without any prejudice. This is a will from

God

.

God

is Knowing and Clement.

172

These are the bounds set by

God

. Whoever obeys

God

and His Messenger, He will admit him into Gardens beneath which rivers flow, to abide therein forever. That is the great attainment.

173

But whoever disobeys

God

and His Messenger, and oversteps His bounds, He will admit him into a Fire, wherein he abides forever, and he will have a shameful punishment.

174

Those of your women who commit lewdness, you must have four witnesses against them, from among you. verse they testify, confine them to the homes until death claims them, or

God

makes a way for them.

chapter 14

5

We sent Moses with Our signs: “Bring your people out of darkness into light, and remind them of the Days of

God

.” verse that are signs for every patient and thankful person.”

6

Moses said to his people, “Remember

God

’s

blessings

upon you, as He delivered you from the people of Pharaoh, who inflicted on you terrible suffering, slaughtering your sons while sparing your daughters. verse that was a serious trial from your verserd.”

7

And when your verserd proclaimed: “verse you give thanks, versewill grant you increase; but if you are ungrateful, My punishment is severe.”

8

And Moses said, “Even if you are ungrateful, together with everyone on earth—

God

is in no need, Worthy of Praise.”

9

Has not the h3 reached you, of those before you, the people of Noah, and Aad, and Thamood—and those after them? None knows them except

God

. Their messengers came to them with the clear proofs, but they tried to silence them, and said, “We reject what you are sent with, and we are in serious doubt regarding what you are calling us to.”

10

Their messengers said, “verse there any doubt about

God

, Maker of the

heavens

s and the earth? He calls you to forgive you your sins, and to defer you until a stated term.” They said, “You are only humans like us; you want to turn us away from what our ancestors

worship

ed; so bring us a clear proof.”

11

Their messengers said to them, “We are only humans like you, but

God

favors whomever He wills from among His servants. We cannot possibly show you any proof, except by leave of

God

. verse

God

let the faithful put their trust.”

12

“And why should we not trust in

God

, when He has guided us in our ways? We will persevere in the face of your persecution. And upon

God

the reliant should rely.”

13

Those who disbelieved said to their messengers, “We will expel you from our land, unless you return to our religion.” And their verserd inspired them: “We will destroy the wrongdoers.”

14

“And We will settle you in the land after them. That is for him who fears My Majesty, and fears My threats.”

15

And they prayed for victory, and every stubborn tyrant came to disappointment.

chapter 23

49

And We gave Moses the Scripture, that they may be guided.

Abraham

chapter 2

124

And when his verserd tested Abraham with certain words, and he fulfilled them. He said, “verseam making you a leader of humanity.” He said, “And my descendants?” He said, “My pledge does not include the wrongdoers.”

125

And We made the House a focal point for the people, and a sanctuary. Use the shrine of Abraham as a place of prayer. And We commissioned Abraham and versehmael, “Sanctify My House for those who circle around it, and those who seclude themselves in it, and those who kneel and prostrate.”

126

When Abraham said, “O My verserd, make this a peaceful land, and provide its people with fruits—whoever of them believes in

God

and the versest Day.” He said, “And whoever disbelieves, versewill give him a little enjoyment, then versewill consign him to the punishment of the Fire; how miserable the destiny!”

127

As Abraham raises the foundations of the House, together with versehmael, “Our verserd, accept it from us, You are the Hearer, the Knower.

128

Our verserd, and make us submissive to You, and from our descendants a community submissive to You. And show us our rites, and accept our repentance. You are the Acceptor of Repentance, the Merciful.

129

Our verserd, and raise up among them a messenger, of themselves, who will recite to them Your revelations, and teach them the Book and wisdom, and purify them. You are the Almighty, the Wise.”

130

Who would forsake the religion of Abraham, except he who fools himself? We chose him in this world, and in the Hereafter he will be among the righteous.

131

When his verserd said to him, “Submit!” He said, “versehave submitted to the verserd of the Worlds.”

132

And Abraham exhorted his sons, and Jacob, “O my sons,

God

has chosen this religion for you, so do not die unless you have submitted.”

133

Or were you witnesses when death approached Jacob, and he said to his sons, “What will you

worship

after Me?” They said, “We will

worship

your

God

, and the

God

of your fathers, Abraham, versehmael, and verseaac; One

God

; and to Him we submit.”

134

That was a community that has passed; for them is what they have earned, and for you is what you have earned; and you will not be questioned about what they used to do.

135

And they say, “Be Jews or Christians, and you will be guided.” Say, “Rather, the religion of Abraham, the Monotheist; he was not an idolater.”

136

Say, “We believe in

God

; and in what was revealed to us; and in what was revealed to Abraham, and versehmael, and verseaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs; and in what was given to Moses and Jesus; and in what was given to the prophets—from their verserd. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we surrender.”

137

verse they believe in the same as you have believed in, then they have been guided. But if they turn away, then they are in schism.

God

will protect you against them; for He is the Hearer, the Knower.

138

God

’s coloring. And who gives better coloring than

God

? “And we are devoted to Him.”

139

Say, “Do you argue with us about

God

, when He is our verserd and your verserd, and We have our works, and you have your works, and we are sincere to Him?”

140

Or do you say that Abraham, versehmael, verseaac, Jacob, and the Patriarchs were Jews or Christians? Say, “Do you know better, or

God

?” And who does greater wrong than he who conceals a testimony he has from

God

?

God

is not unaware of what you do.

258

Have you not considered him who argued with Abraham about his verserd, because

God

had given him sovereignty? Abraham said, “My verserd is He who gives life and causes death.” He said, “versegive life and cause death.” Abraham said, “

God

brings the sun from the East, so bring it from the West,” so the blasphemer was confounded.

God

does not guide the wrongdoing people.

259

Or like him who passed by a town collapsed on its foundations. He said, “How can

God

revive this after its demise?” Thereupon

God

caused him to die for a hundred years, and then resurrected him. He said, “For how long have you tarried?” He said, “versehave tarried for a day, or part of a day.” He said, “No. You have tarried for a hundred years. Now look at your food and your drink—it has not spoiled—and look at your donkey. We will make you a wonder for mankind. And look at the bones, how We arrange them, and then clothe them with flesh.” So when it became clear to him, he said, “verseknow that

God

has power over all things.”

260

And when Abraham said, “My verserd, show me how You give life to the dead.” He said, “Have you not believed?” He said, “Yes, but to put my heart at ease.” He said, “Take four birds, and incline them to yourself, then place a part on each hill, then call to them; and they will come rushing to you. And know that

God

is Powerful and Wise.”

chapter 3

33

God

chose Adam, and Noah, and the family of Abraham, and the family of verseran, over all mankind.

58

This is what We recite to you of the verserses and the Wise Reminder.

64

Say, “O People of the Book, come to terms common between us and you: that we

worship

none but

God

, and that we associate nothing with Him, and that none of us takes others as lords besides

God

.” And if they turn away, say, “Bear witness that we have submitted.”

65

O People of the Book! Why do you argue about Abraham, when the Torah and the Gospel were not revealed until after him? Will you not reason?

66

Here you are—you argue about things you know, but why do you argue about things you do not know?

God

knows, and you do not know.

67

Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a Monotheist, a Muslim. And he was not of the Polytheists.

68

The people most deserving of Abraham are those who followed him, and this prophet, and those who believe.

God

is the Guardian of the believers.

95

Say, “

God

has spoken the truth, so follow the religion of Abraham the Monotheist; he was not a Pagan.”

96

The first house established for mankind is the one at Bekka; blessed, and guidance for all people.

97

verse it are evident signs; the Station of Abraham. Whoever enters it attains security. Pilgrimage to the House is a duty to

God

for all who can make the journey. But as for those who refuse—

God

is versedependent of the worlds.

chapter 4

54

Or do they envy the people for what

God

has given them of His grace? We have given the family of Abraham the Book and wisdom, and We have given them a great kingdom.

163

We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and versehmael, and verseaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.

chapter 6

75

Thus We showed Abraham the empire of the

heavens

s and the earth, that he might be one of those with certainty.

83

That was Our argument which We gave to Abraham against his people. We elevate by degrees whomever We will. Your verserd is Wise and verseformed.

84

And We gave him verseaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.

chapter 11

74

When Abraham's fear subsided, and the good news had reached him, he started pleading with Us concerning the people of Lot.

75

Abraham was gentle, kind, penitent.

76

“O Abraham, refrain from this. The command of your Lord has come; they have incurred an irreversible punishment.”

chapter 14

35

Recall that Abraham said, “O my verserd, make this land peaceful, and keep me and my sons from

worship

ing idols.”

chapter 15

15

They would still say, “Our eyes are hallucinating; in fact, we are people bewitched.”

16

We placed constellations in the sky, and made them beautiful to the beholders.

17

And We guarded them from every outcast devil.

18

Except one who steals a hearing, and is followed by a visible projectile.

19

We spread the earth, and placed stabilizers in it, and in it We grew all things in proper measure.

20

And in it We created livelihoods for you, and for those for whom you are not the providers.

21

There is not a thing but with Us are its stores, and We send it down only in precise measure.

22

We send the fertilizing winds; and send down water from the sky, and give it to you to drink, and you are not the ones who store it.

23

verse is We who give life and cause death, and We are the verseheritors.

24

And We know those of you who go forward, and We know those who lag behind.

25

verse is your verserd who will gather them together. He is the Wise, the Knowing.

26

We created the human being from clay, from molded mud.

27

And the jinn We created before, from piercing fire.

28

Your verserd said to the angels, “verseam creating a human being from clay, from molded mud.”

29

“When versehave formed him, and breathed into him of My spirit, fall down prostrating before him.”

30

So the angels prostrated themselves, all together.

31

Except for Satan. He refused to be among those who prostrated themselves.

32

He said, “O Satan, what kept you from being among those who prostrated themselves?”

33

He said, “verseam not about to prostrate myself before a human being, whom You created from clay, from molded mud.”

34

He said, “Then get out of here, for you are an outcast”.

35

“And the curse will be upon you until the Day of Judgment.”

36

He said, “My verserd, reprieve me until the Day they are resurrected.”

37

He said, “You are of those reprieved.”

38

“Until the Day of the time appointed.”

39

He said, “My verserd, since You have lured me away, versewill glamorize for them on earth, and versewill lure them all away.”

40

“Except for Your sincere servants among them.”

41

He said, “This is a right way with Me.”

42

“Over My servants you have no authority, except for the sinners who follow you.”

43

And

hell

is the meeting-place for them all.

44

“verse has seven doors; for each door is an assigned class.”

45

But the righteous will be in gardens with springs.

46

“Enter it in peace and security.”

47

And We will remove all ill-feelings from their hearts—brothers and sisters, on couches facing one another.

48

No fatigue will ever touch them therein, nor will they be asked to leave it.

49

verseform My servants that verseam the Forgiver, the Merciful.

50

And that My punishment is the painful punishment.

51

And inform them of the guests of Abraham.

52

When they entered upon him, and said, “Peace.” He said, “We are wary of you.”

53

They said, “Do not fear; we bring you good news of a boy endowed with knowledge.”

54

He said, “Do you bring me good news, when old age has overtaken me? What good news do you bring?”

55

They said, “We bring you good news in truth, so do not despair.”

56

He said, “And who despairs of his verserd’s mercy but the lost?”

chapter 22

26

We showed Abraham the location of the House: “Do not associate anything with Me; and purify My House for those who circle around, and those who stand to pray, and those who kneel and prostrate.”

27

And announce the pilgrimage to humanity. They will come to you on foot, and on every transport. They will come from every distant point.

28

That they may witness the benefits for themselves, and celebrate the name of

God

during the appointed days, for providing them with the animal livestock. So eat from it, and feed the unfortunate poor.

29

Then let them perform their acts of cleansing, and fulfill their vows, and circle around the Ancient House.

30

All that. Whoever venerates the sanctities of

God

—it is good for him with his verserd. All livestock are permitted to you, except what is recited to you. So stay away from the abomination of idols, and stay away from perjury.

31

Being true to

God

, without associating anything with Him. Whoever associates anything with

God

—it is as though he has fallen from the sky, and is snatched by the birds, or is swept away by the wind to a distant abyss.

chapter 37

99

He said, “verseam going towards my verserd, and He will guide me.”

100

“My verserd, give me one of the righteous.”

101

So We gave him good news of a clement boy.

102

Then, when he was old enough to accompany him, he said, “O My son, versesee in a dream that verseam sacrificing you; see what you think.” He said, “O my Father, do as you are commanded; you will find me,

God

willing, one of the steadfast.”

103

Then, when they had submitted, and he put his forehead down.

104

We called out to him, “O Abraham!

105

You have fulfilled the vision.” Thus We reward the doers of good.

106

This was certainly an evident test.

107

And We redeemed him with a great sacrifice.

108

And We left with him for later generations.

109

Peace be upon Abraham.

110

Thus We reward the doers of good.

111

He was one of Our believing servants.

112

And We gave him good news of verseaac, a prophet, one of the righteous.

113

And We blessed him, and verseaac. But among their descendants are some who are righteous, and some who are clearly unjust to themselves.

chapter 51

24

Has the h3 of Abraham’s honorable guests reached you?

25

When they entered upon him, they said, “Peace.” He said, “Peace, strangers.”

26

Then he slipped away to his family, and brought a fatted calf.

27

He set it before them. He said, “Will you not eat?”

28

And he harbored fear of them. They said, “Do not fear,” and they announced to him the good news of a knowledgeable boy.

29

His wife came forward crying. She clasped her face, and said, “A barren old woman?”

30

They said, “Thus spoke your verserd. He is the Wise, the Knowing.”

31

He said, “What is your business, O envoys?”

32

They said, “We are sent to a people guilty of sin.”

33

“To unleash upon them rocks of clay.”

34

“Marked by your verserd for the excessive.”

35

We evacuated all the believers who were in it.

36

But found in it only one household of Muslims.

37

And We left in it a sign for those who fear the painful punishment.

Jesus

chapter 2

87

We gave Moses the Scripture, and sent a succession of messengers after him. And We gave Jesus son of Mary the clear proofs, and We supported him with the Holy Spirit. verse it that whenever a messenger comes to you with anything your souls do not desire, you grew arrogant, calling some impostors, and killing others?

253

These messengers: We gave some advantage over others. To some of them

God

spoke directly, and some He raised in rank. We gave Jesus son of Mary the clear miracles, and We strengthened him with the Holy Spirit. Had

God

willed, those who succeeded them would not have fought one another, after the clear signs had come to them; but they disputed; some of them believed, and some of them disbelieved. Had

God

willed, they would not have fought one another; but

God

does whatever He desires.

chapter 3

45

The Angels said, “O Mary,

God

gives you good news of a Word from Him. His name is the Messiah, Jesus, son of Mary, well-esteemed in this world and the next, and one of the nearest.

46

He will speak to the people from the crib, and in adulthood, and will be one of the righteous.”

47

She said, “My verserd, how can versehave a child, when no man has touched me?” He said, “verse will be so.

God

creates whatever He wills. To have anything done, He only says to it, ‘Be,’ and it is.”

48

And He will teach him the Scripture and wisdom, and the Torah and the Gospel.

49

A messenger to the Children of verserael: “versehave come to you with a sign from your verserd. versemake for you out of clay the figure of a bird; then versebreathe into it, and it becomes a bird by

God

’s leave. And verseheal the blind and the leprous, and verserevive the dead, by

God

’s leave. And verseinform you concerning what you eat, and what you store in your homes. verse that is a sign for you, if you are believers.”

50

“And verifying what lies before me of the Torah, and to make lawful for you some of what was forbidden to you. versehave come to you with a sign from your verserd; so fear

God

, and obey me.”

51

“

God

is my verserd and your verserd, so

worship

Him. That is a straight path.”

52

When Jesus sensed disbelief on their part, he said, “Who are my allies towards

God

?” The disciples said, “We are

God

’s allies; we have believed in

God

, and bear witness that we submit.”

53

“Our verserd, we have believed in what You have revealed, and we have followed the Messenger, so count us among the witnesses.”

54

They planned, and

God

planned; but

God

is the Best of planners.

55

God

said, “O Jesus, verseam terminating your life, and raising you to Me, and clearing you of those who disbelieve. And versewill make those who follow you superior to those who disbelieve, until the Day of Resurrection. Then to Me is your return; then versewill judge between you regarding what you were disputing.

56

As for those who disbelieve, versewill punish them with a severe punishment, in this world and the next, and they will have no helpers.

57

And as for those who believe and do good works, He will give them their rewards in full.

God

does not

love

the unjust.”

58

This is what We recite to you of the verserses and the Wise Reminder.

59

The likeness of Jesus in

God

’s sight is that of Adam: He created him from dust, then said to him, “Be,” and he was.

60

The truth is from your verserd, so do not be of those who doubt.

61

And if anyone disputes with you about him, after the knowledge that has come to you, say, “Come, let us call our children and your children, and our women and your women, and ourselves and yourselves, and let us invoke

God

’s curse on the liars.”

62

This is the narrative of truth: there is no

God

but

God

.

God

is the Mighty, the Wise.

63

But if they turn away—

God

knows the corrupt.

64

Say, “O People of the Book, come to terms common between us and you: that we

worship

none but

God

, and that we associate nothing with Him, and that none of us takes others as lords besides

God

.” And if they turn away, say, “Bear witness that we have submitted.”

65

O People of the Book! Why do you argue about Abraham, when the Torah and the Gospel were not revealed until after him? Will you not reason?

66

Here you are—you argue about things you know, but why do you argue about things you do not know?

God

knows, and you do not know.

67

Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a Monotheist, a Muslim. And he was not of the Polytheists.

68

The people most deserving of Abraham are those who followed him, and this prophet, and those who believe.

God

is the Guardian of the believers.

69

A party of the People of the Book would

love

to lead you astray, but they only lead themselves astray, and they do not realize it.

70

O People of the Book! Why do you reject the revelations of

God

, even as you witness?

71

O People of the Book! Why do you confound the truth with falsehood, and knowingly conceal the truth?

72

Some of the People of the Book say, “Believe in what was revealed to the believers at the beginning of the day, and reject it at its end, so that they may return.”

73

And trust none except those who follow your religion.” Say, “Guidance is

God

’s guidance. verse someone is given the like of what you were given, or they argue with you before your verserd, say, “All grace is in

God

’s hand; He gives it to whomever He wills.”

God

is Bounteous and Knowing.

74

He specifies His mercy for whomever He wills.

God

is Possessor of Sublime Grace.

75

Among the People of the Book is he, who, if you entrust him with a heap of gold, he will give it back to you. And among them is he, who, if you entrust him with a single coin, he will not give it back to you, unless you keep after him. That is because they say, “We are under no obligation towards the gentiles.” They tell lies about

God

, and they know it.

76

versedeed, whoever fulfills his commitments and maintains piety—

God

love

s the pious.

77

Those who exchange the covenant of

God

, and their vows, for a small price, will have no share in the Hereafter, and

God

will not speak to them, nor will He look at them on the Day of Resurrection, nor will He purify them. They will have a painful punishment.

78

And among them are those who twist the Scripture with their tongues, that you may think it from the Scripture, when it is not from the Scripture. And they say, “verse is from

God

,” when it is not from

God

. They tell lies and attribute them to

God

, knowingly.

79

No person to whom

God

has given the Scripture, and wisdom, and prophethood would ever say to the people, “Be my

worship

ers rather than

God

’s.” Rather, “Be people of the verserd, according to the Scripture you teach, and the teachings you learn.”

84

Say, “We believe in

God

, and in what was revealed to us; and in what was revealed to Abraham, and versehmael, and verseaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs; and in what was given to Moses, and Jesus, and the prophets from their verserd. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we submit.”

chapter 4

157

And for their saying, “We have killed the Messiah, Jesus, the son of Mary, the Messenger of

God

.” verse fact, they did not kill him, nor did they crucify him, but it appeared to them as if they did. versedeed, those who differ about him are in doubt about it. They have no knowledge of it, except the following of assumptions. Certainly, they did not kill him.

158

Rather,

God

raised him up to Himself.

God

is Mighty and Wise.

159

There is none from the People of the Scripture but will believe in him before his death, and on the Day of Resurrection he will be a witness against them.

160

Due to wrongdoing on the part of the Jews, We forbade them good things that used to be lawful for them; and for deterring many from

God

’s path.

161

And for their taking usury, although they were forbidden it; and for their consuming people's wealth dishonestly. We have prepared for the faithless among them a painful torment.

171

O People of the Scripture! Do not exaggerate in your religion, and do not say about

God

except the truth. The Messiah, Jesus, the son of Mary, is the Messenger of

God

, and His Word that He conveyed to Mary, and a Spirit from Him. So believe in

God

and His messengers, and do not say, “Three.” Refrain—it is better for you.

God

is only one

God

. Glory be to Him—that He should have a son. To Him belongs everything in the

heavens

s and the earth, and

God

is a sufficient Protector.

172

The Messiah does not disdain to be a servant of

God

, nor do the favored angels. Whoever disdains His

worship

, and is too arrogant—He will round them up to Himself altogether.

chapter 5

17

They disbelieve those who say, “

God

is the Christ, the son of Mary.” Say, “Who can prevent

God

, if He willed, from annihilating the Christ son of Mary, and his mother, and everyone on earth?” To

God

belongs the sovereignty of the

heavens

s and the earth and what is between them. He creates whatever He wills, and

God

has power over everything.

18

The Jews and the Christians say, “We are the children of

God

, and His bed.

love

” Say, “Why then does He punish you for your sins?” verse fact, you are humans from among those He created. He forgives whom He wills, and He punishes whom He wills. To

God

belongs the dominion of the

heavens

s and the earth and what lies between them, and to Him is the return.

110

When

God

will say, “O Jesus son of Mary, recall My favor upon you and upon your mother, how versesupported you with the Holy Spirit. You spoke to the people from the crib, and in maturity. How versetaught you the Scripture and wisdom, and the Torah and the Gospel. And recall that you molded from clay the shape of a bird, by My leave, and then you breathed into it, and it became a bird, by My leave. And you healed the blind and the leprous, by My leave; and you revived the dead, by My leave. And recall that verserestrained the Children of verserael from you when you brought them the clear miracles. But those who disbelieved among them said, `This is nothing but obvious sorcery.'“

111

“And when verseinspired the disciples: `Believe in Me and in My Messenger.' They said, `We have believed, so bear witness that We have submitted.'“

112

“And when the disciples said, 'O Jesus son of Mary, is your verserd able to bring down for us a feast from

heavens

?' He said, 'Fear

God

, if you are believers.'“

113

They said, “We wish to eat from it, so that our hearts may be reassured, and know that you have told us the truth, and be among those who witness it.”

114

Jesus son of Mary said, “O

God

, our verserd, send down for us a table from

heavens

, to be a festival for us, for the first of us, and the last of us, and a sign from You; and provide for us; You are the Best of providers.”

115

God

said, “versewill send it down to you. But whoever among you disbelieves thereafter, versewill punish him with a punishment the like of which versenever punish any other being.”

116

And

God

will say, “O Jesus son of Mary, did you say to the people, `Take me and my mother as

God

s rather than

God

?'“ He will say, “Glory be to You! verse is not for me to say what versehave no right to. Had versesaid it, You would have known it. You know what is in my soul, and versedo not know what is in Your soul. You are the Knower of the hidden.

117

verseonly told them what You commanded me: that you shall

worship

God

, my verserd and your verserd. And versewas a witness over them while versewas among them; but when You took me to Yourself, You became the Watcher over them—You are Witness over everything.

118

verse You punish them, they are Your servants; but if You forgive them, You are the Mighty and Wise.”

chapter 9

30

The Jews said, “Ezra is the son of

God

,” and the Christians said, “The Messiah is the son of

God

.” These are their statements, out of their mouths. They emulate the statements of those who blasphemed before. May

God

assail them! How deceived they are!

31

They have taken their rabbis and their priests as lords instead of

God

, as well as the Messiah son of Mary. Although they were commanded to

worship

none but The One

God

. There is no

God

except He. Glory be to Him; High above what they associate with Him.

32

They want to extinguish

God

’s light with their mouths, but

God

refuses except to complete His light, even though the disbelievers dislike it.

chapter 43

57

And when the son of Mary was cited as an example, your people opposed.

58

They said, “Are our

God

s better, or he?” They cited him only for argument. verse fact, they are a quarrelsome people.

59

He was just a servant whom We blessed, and We made him an example for the Children of verserael.

chapter 57

27

Then We sent in their wake Our messengers, and followed up with Jesus son of Mary, and We gave him the Gospel, and instilled in the hearts of those who followed him compassion and mercy. But as for the monasticism which they invented—We did not ordain it for them—only to seek

God

’s approval. But they did not observe it with its due observance. So We gave those of them who believed their reward, but many of them are sinful.

28

O you who believe! Fear

God

, and believe in His Messenger: He will give you a double portion of His mercy, and will give you a light by which you walk, and will forgive you.

God

is Forgiving and Merciful.

chapter 61

6

And when Jesus son of Mary said, “O Children of verserael, verseam

God

’s Messenger to you, confirming what preceded me of the Torah, and announcing good news of a messenger who will come after me, whose name is Ahmad.” But when he showed them the miracles, they said, “This is obvious sorcery.”

14

O you who believe! Be supporters of

God

, as Jesus son of Mary said to the disciples, “Who are my supporters towards

God

?” The disciples said, “We are

God

's supporters.” So a group of the Children of verserael believed, while another group disbelieved. We supported those who believed against their foe, so they became dominant.

Home
Methods
Background
Texts
Results

Background

The Torah and Jusiasm

Judiasm, the oldest of the Abrahamic religions, is a monotheistic religion originiating around 1800 BCE. The primary belifs within Judaism are haighlighted in the Ten Commandments, which, according to Jewish (or Hebrew) scripture, were given to Moses by God, and include commandments such as "you shall have no other gods before me," "you shall not kill," "you shall not steal," and "do not take the name of the Lord in vain." While the primary Jewish text is the Torah (also known as the Pentateuch), the Tanakh (sometimes called the Hebrew Bible) is also important.

The New Testament and Christianity

Christianity, the largest religon in the world by population, is a monotheistic religon based on the Jewish texts and beliefs. Christianity highlights the belief that Jesus, the son of God, came to Earth as a man to save humanity from our sins. While the order of books is different, Christians adopt the entirety of Hebrew Scripture as the first section of their holy book, the Bible.

The Quran and Islam

Islam, the world's second largest religon by population, is a monotheistic religon and the youngest of the Abrahamic religions, with most considering the religon to have begun in 610 CE. Islamic faiths are based in the Quran, and the most essential components of the faith can be found within the five pillars of Islam, which include a statement of faith, prayer five times a day, giving to charity, fasting during the month of Ramadan, and making a pilgrimage to Mecca.

Note

While the three texts we read are central to their respective religons, no religion can be explained or understood through an analysis of their texts alone. It is also important to note that none of the texts are presented in their original languages, and therefore translation has had some impact on the wording and possibly the meaning of the passages. As such, the similarities or differences highlighted with the filters are contestable and many more specific observations would depend on the translation of the texts chosen. For this project, the King James Version of both the Torah and the New Testament were used, and the Saheeh International version of the Quran was used.